Hello. My name is David Silver.
こんにちはデイビッド シルバーです
I am the team lead for the self-driving car in Nanodegree program here at Udacity.
Udacity Nanodegree プログラムの自動運転車のチームリーダーです
Hey, I'm Aaron Brown.
こんにちは アーロン ブラウンです
I'm a content developer and I helped built
わたしはコンテンツ開発者です
the project that we're going to be walking through today, which is path planning.
今日 皆さんと見ていくパスプランニングプロジェクトの構築に携わりました
That's right. This is the walk through for the path planning project,
そうですこれがパスプランニングプロジェクトのウォークスルーになります
which is the first project in term two.
Term 2 最初のプロジェクトです
And, the only project in the path planning module of the self-driving car program.
自動運転車プログラムのパスプランニングモジュールでは唯一のプロジェクトになります
So, let's get started.
それでは始めましょう
Aaron, you built this.
アーロン 君が作ったんですよね
Where do I get started?
どこから始めればいいですか?
Should I get started in the classroom?
クラスムールから始ますか?
Yeah. So, let's go ahead and get started by checking out the project repository.
そうですねでは まず プロジェクトのリポジトリをチェックアウトするところから始めましょう
Okay. All right.
OKわかりました
Windisk.
Windisk
Udacity path planning project and that should come up on Google, right? Yeah.
Udacity パスプランニングプロジェクト これで Google 検索できるかなあった
Yeah. First hit.
あった先頭に出てきましたね
First hit. Okay.
最初に出てきましたねOK
Cool.
よし いいですね
This will have all the code that we need to get
ここには始めるにあたって必要なコードがすべてあります
started including the link to download the simulator.
シミュレーターをダウンロードするリンクもあります
Okay. So, let's see.
OKそれでは
I've already downloaded the simulator.
シミュレーター 私は既にダウンロードしておきました
So, we download the simulator.
そう シミュレーターをダウンロードします
What should we do next?
次は何をすればいいですか?
Well, we can actually just clone this repository over.
では このリポジトリのクローンを作成しましょう
Okay.
OK
And, start building some code for our path planner.
それから パスプランナー用のコードを作成し始めましょう
Got it. So, we could clone the repo.
了解リポジトリのクローン作成ですね
I've already done that as well,
これもやっておきましたよ
here in my terminal.
これが私のターミナルです
I am in the CarND path planning project directory.
現在 CarND-Path-Planning-Project のディレクトリにいます
Actually, within the source,
実際にはソース内
sub-directory of that project.
このプロジェクトのサブディレクトリにいます
Okay.
了解
So, what next?
では 次は?
Well, in source, all your main code will be coming from main.cpp.
ソース内のメインコードは main.cpp からのコードを使用します
Okay.
了解
There's also some instructions in the Read Me as
また Read Me にも開始する上での説明や
well for just getting started and, what you, kind of,
シミュレーターから C++ コードに移行する場合に考慮すべき
need to be thinking about when you're going from your simulator to your C++ code.
ことが記載されています
Okay. So here, we talk about cloning the repo,
了解ここですね リポジトリのクローンを作成する
talk about how to build the repo, and how to run it.
リポジトリをビルドする コードを実行する それぞれを見ていくことにします
Yeah.
了解
Just to make sure,
オリジナルの状態
I'm also, kind of,
にいることを
in an original state.
確認します
I'll check out main.cpp from the repo. I'll come over here.
リポジトリから main.cpp をチェックアウトしますこちらに移動します
I've already run CMake.
cmake は実行済みなので
So now, I can just make the project as is.
プロジェクトをそのまま make します
Make sure it compiles.
正常にコンパイルしていることを確認してくださいね
And, I'll run the binary.
バイナリを実行します
So now, we're running the path planning binary.
これで パスプランニングのバイナリが実行しています
I'll swipe over and let's run the simulator.
こっちの画面にスワイプしてシミュレーターを動かしてみます
Yeah.
了解
So what's going to happen?
何が起きるのですか?
That car is just going to sit there.
車は停止したまま動きません
It has an empty list of xy points.
xy ポイントのリストが空のためです
That seems disappointing.
がっかりですね
Yeah. So, we need to add some xy points to our planner.
そうですねそのため xy ポイントをプランナーに追加する必要があります
Okay. So, how do we do that?
了解では どうしたらいいですか?
Should we go to the classroom? Should we do something else?
クラスムールに行きますか?別の方法がありますか?
Well, let's open up main.cpp.
main.cpp を開いてみましょう
When we first open it up,
初めて main.cpp を開くと
we'll see a number of helper functions that we have at our disposal.
自由に使えるヘルパー関数が表示されます
Okay. Let's look at those helper functions.
OKこのヘルパー関数を見てみることにしましょう
Let's look at the helper functions.
このヘルパー関数を見てみます
There's a hasData helper function.
hasData ヘルパー関数というのがあります
Are we going to need this?
この関数は必要ですか?
This is actually something that comes from our uWebSocket template
これは uWebSocket テンプレートからの関数ですね
that we've seen in other projects before.
別のプロジェクトでも見たことがありますね
Okay.
了解
We have distance.
distance があります
So, that could be helpful.
役に立ちそうですね
So, that's calculating Euclidean distance between two points.
2 点のユークリッド距離を計算します
Yeah. A lot of geometry is happening in this project.
了解このプロジェクトではたくさんの幾何学を使用します
Okay.
了解
Closest waypoint.
ClosestWaypoint
We have a map of all these waypoints around our highway.
幹線道路付近のすべてのウェイポイントを含む地図があります
Okay.
了解
We can see which one is closest to us.
一番近いウェイポイントを確認することができます
We can see which is the next waypoint.
どれが NextWaypoint になるかも確認できます
What's the difference between closest and the next waypoint?
ClosestWaypoint と NextWaypoint の違いは何ですか
Because you could be right in front of a waypoint,
ウェイポイントのちょうど前にいるとします
and your angle is telling you that you want to go to this one that's further out,
角度が 近いけれど現在の地点より後ろにあるウェイポイントではなく
instead of the one that's closer to you but behind you.
少し遠いけれど向かうのはこっちのウェイポイントだと示している場合です
Got it. It's like on the airplane where the nearest exit might be behind you.
そういうことですね飛行機に乗ったときに 一番近い出口が後方にある可能性があるのと似ていますね
Yeah.
そのとおりです
Got it. Okay.
了解しましたOK
Let's see.
では
GetFrenet.
getFrenet
Yeah. So, In the path planning lesson,
そうですねパスプランニングのレッスンでは
we talked a lot about frenet coordinates and how
frenet 座標についていろいろと見てきました
they can be really helpful especially in a highway.
また frenet 座標が特に幹線道路で非常に役立つことも説明しました
So, we had these transformations from going from frenet coordinates to xy coordinates.
これらの転換は frenet 座標から xy 座標への移行で行っています
Got it. What are the arguments here?
了解引数についてはどうですか
There are five arguments. What are they?
引数は 5 つありますどのような引数ですか?
Well, we can have the ones that you'd expect like x and y.
x と y など皆さんが期待するような引数のほか
We also have data because this is helpful for
theta もあります
actually doing the transformation if you look at the map.
地図を見ている場合 実際に変換を行う際に便利です
And, we also have these list of
また x と y のウェイポイントのリストもあります
x and y waypoints that we calculate at the very beginning.
ウェイポイントは最初に計算します
Got it. Okay. So, which of these do we need to worry about and which of these do we just,
OKでは この中のどれに注目する必要がありますか
kind of, pass in without thinking too much about?
また あまり気にする必要のないものはありますか
Xy and theta.
x y と theta です
Okay.
OK
And, basically, just use
あとは 基本的に 最初に maps_x とmaps_y
whatever we calculate at the very beginning for the maps x and maps y.
に計算したものを使用します
Okay.
了解
That comes from a file to the map.
ファイルから地図へ出力されます
And, do we need to worry too much or at all
getFrenet 内で起こっていることを
about what's going on inside of getFrenet or do we just use it,
実際に理解しておく必要がありますか?
kind of, as a black box?
あるいはブラックボックスと理解してそのまま使用するだけでいいですか?
You can use it as a black box,
特に理解しなくても使用できます
but the code is definitely there where you can actually modify it.
ただし コードには実際にアクセスすることができ 修正することも可能です
And, maybe you can even make it better,
コードを改善することも可能です
maybe you have a different idea for how you want to do the transformation.
変換方法に別のアイデアを取り入れることもできます
Okay.
OK
Yeah. There's a lot of freedom there.
本当に さまざまな修正や変更を行うことができます
Okay. So, let's see.
OK 見てみましょう
We did getFrenet and this is getXY.
getFrenet は見たので 今度は getXY です
Got it.
そうですね
This should be the inverse, except that,
これは逆変換のはずです ただし、
Frenet and xy are not, completely.
Frenet と xy は正確には
It's not a linear transformation, exactly.
線形変換ではありません
Got it. So, instead of passing an x and y,
わかりましたx と y を渡す代わりに
we pass an s and d, which are the Frenet coordinates.
s と d を渡します Frenet の座標です
And, instead of passing on theta,
また theta に渡す代わりに
we pass in this vector maps s.
このベクターの maps_s に渡します
Yes.
はい
And then, again, maps x and y.
そして maps_x と maps_y にも渡します
Is maps s something we need to worry about? Or is that just at the beginning?
maps_s で何か注意する必要はありますか?最初の計算のままでいいですか?
That something that's calculated at the very beginning that we can just feed it.
これは最初に計算されるので それを与えるだけで
And, that's just used for the map inside the function itself.
関数内の地図にそのまま使用されます
Got it. Okay. And now, we get to main.
わかりましたOKでは main を見ていきます
So, those are all the helper functions. This is main.
これはすべてヘルパー関数ですこれが main です
Yeah.
そうですね
Look's like there's a lot of variables being declared here.
かなり多くの変数が宣言されているように見えます
There are a couple of constants.
定数がいくつかあります
There's the CSV file.
CSV ファイルがあります
There's the link for the track it looks like.
トラックのリンクがあります
Which can be helpful when you're wrapping background.
これはラップアラウンドする際に便利です
Okay.
OK
But, we just go ahead and we open up that text file for a map,
先に進んで地図のテキストファイルを開き
and we load up our vector a doubles of x,
x, y, s, dx, dyからなる
y, s, dx, and dy.
ベクターをロードします
Dx and dy is just that normal component to that waypoint.
dx および dy は単にそのウェイポイントに対する通常の成分です
Got it. Where do we open up the CSV file?
わかりましたCSV ファイルはどこで開きますか?
It's actually just coming from data and it's called highwaymap.csv.
実際にはデータから取得します highwaymap.csv と呼ばれています
So, we're using our stringstream to actually load that up.
stringstream を使用してロードします
Got it. So, that's done for us.
了解これも実行済みです
Yeah. Then we can just use it throughout the program.
そうですねでは それをプログラムでは使用していきましょう
Okay. Let's see. So now,
了解では えっと
there's a message passing.
メッセージが渡されていますね
What's going on here?
何が起きているんですか
Once we get passed the usual uWebSocket template,
いつもの uWebSocket テンプレートを渡したら
we actually get our localization data.
ローカライゼーションデータが得られます
Okay.
了解
So, the simulator is telling us exactly where
シミュレーターは Frenet の sd と xy で
the xy and sd Frenet coordinates of the car are at.
車両の正確な位置を示しています
Okay.
了解
Along with the car's angle and the car's speed.
車両の角度と速度についても示しています
So, there's this,
ここなんですが
if event equals telemetry function,
if (event == "telemetry") があって
and is this space to where the action is happening?
ここがアクションを発生させている箇所ですか？
Yeah. So, this is all the variables that we're going to be working with in
はいエンジニアリング的に重要な部分を
order to decide how we want to be creating engineering points.
どのようにするか決定するために使用する全ての変数がここにあります
Got it. Okay. So, a bunch of variables getting defined here,
了解わかりました一連の変数がここで指定され
some Json stuff getting defined.
JSON も指定されていますね
Sensor fusion is pretty important as well.
センサーフュージョンも重要です
So, we talked about localization.
ローカライゼーションについて説明しました
Sensor fusion's all the other cars on the road with us,
センサーフュージョンは路上にある他の全車両です
that we don't want to crash into,
これらの車両とぶつかりたくないですよね
that we want to try to pass when possible.
できればよけたいですよね
Got it. So, there's this, TODO here and it says,
了解ここ ここに TODO があります こう書いてあります
"Define a path made up of (x,y) points that the car
(日本語訳: 「車が .02 秒ごと連続的に
will visit sequentially every .02 seconds."
進む (x,y) ポイントで構成されるパスを定義します 」)
And then, underneath the TODO,
この TODO の下に
we are setting some Json variables that looks like equal to our x vals and y vals,
JSON 変数を設定しています
or next x vals and xy vals.
x vals と y vals または next_x_vals と next_y_vals と同等のようですね
And, that makes up our path planner.
それがパスプランナーを構成しています
Got it.
了解
X and y points.
x と y ポイントです
So, in order to get the car to move forward,
車両を前進させるには
we have to set these next x vals,
これらの next_x_vals や next_y_vals に
next y vals to something because right now we're just declaring them,
何かを設定しないといけないわけですね
and immediately, we're using them.
現在は この状態のまま使用しているわけですね
Yeah. Hence, the reason our cars are sitting still at the moment.
そのとおりですさっき見たように 私たちの車が停止したままなのは これが原因です
Got it. So, there's nothing in these vectors and so,
わかりましたベクターに何もないから
the car is not going anywhere.
車はどこにも行かないわけですね
Right.
そのとおりです
Okay. So, how do we make the car go somewhere?
OKでは どうしたら車を動かすことができますか?
Well, there's some starter code in the classroom.
クラスルームに開始コードがあります
I was hoping you would say that. All right.
そう言ってくれると思ってましたよ了解
So, this is the first concept in the classroom.
では これがクラスルームの最初のコンセプトです
There's a, kind of, cool GIF here,
ここには便利な GIF があります
talks about the 50-mile an hour speed limit.
時速 50 マイルの速度制限について書かれています
Yeah. And that's, kind of, illustrating the perfect controller.
はい理想的なコントローラーの例が示されています
The car is just going to go exactly at the point that you give
車は与えたポイントに正確に移動しています
it and its angle is going to line up to the points.
角度もポイントで示されています
Got it. Who really cares?
了解どうでもいいんだけど
I just want to get my car to go somewhere.
とにかく自分の車が動いてほしいな
Well, luckily, it's only,
幸運なことに必要なのは
like, six lines of code.
6 行のコードだけなんですよ
Okay. These six lines of code?
OKこの 6 行のことですか?
Yes.
はい そうです
These six lines of code. All right. Let's type these and see what we get.
この 6 行ですね了解では これを入力して どうなるか見てみましょう
Yeah. Go ahead and copy that.
はいさっそくコピーしてみます
Just copy these in.
これをコピーして
So, maybe I'll put these down here.
ここに置きます
Maybe I'll just put END here.
END をここにします
And, just get the formatting a little bit better.
見やすいように整えます
All right. So, let's see, what's going on here?
できましたでは これを見ていきます
We have a double called, distance increment,
double dist_inc = 0.5 とありますが
I guess, that is 0.5 meters.
0.5 は 0.5 メートルですね
Yes. So, that's how much the points are going to be spaced apart.
はいポイントとポイントの間隔になります
Got it. And why 0.5?
了解なぜ 0.5 にしているのですか?
Is that because this is 50 miles an hour basically?
速度制限が時速 50 マイルになっているからですか?
Yes, it's pretty close to 50 miles per hour, it turns out to be.
そうですね 結果 時速 50 マイルにかなり近くなりましたね
Got it. And then we are iterating through a loop 50 times?
了解ループを 50 回繰り返していますね?
Yes. So we're going to be using a constant size of 50 points for a pack planner.
はいパスプランナーに対して 50 ポイントの固定サイズを使用しています
Got it. So, the next_x_vals vector and
了解next_x_vals ベクターと next_y_vals ベクターには
the next_y_vals vector each going to have 50 numbers in them,
それぞれ 50個の数値を持たせ
so that will be 50 points total when you combine the vectors.
ベクターを結合したときに合計 50 ポイントになるようにしているわけですね
Each time we're just pushing back kind of this weird calculation
毎回 ちょっと変わった計算 (car_x+(dist_ inc*i)*cos(deg2rad(car_yaw)
(car_x+(dist_ inc*i)*cos(deg2rad(car_yaw). What is that doing?
を push_back していますが これは何をしているんですか?
Well, that's just a little bit trigger right there since our car has some angle,
それはちょっとしたトリガーですね 車に角度があるためです
we want to be going at that angle constantly,
一定速度の直線で常に
in a straight line with constant velocity.
その角度を維持するためです
Got it.
了解
Constant velocity comes from the fact that we're using the said distance increment.
先ほどの dist_inc を使用しているため一定速度になります
Got it. So, if I make this and run it,
了解では make して実行すると
the car is going to go in a straight line?
車は直線を進むわけですね?
Yes.
はい
Do you promise?
本当に?
Let's see, probably should have set up beforehand, all right.
やってみましょう おっと 事前に準備しておくべきでした よし
So let's run our path planner.
ではパスプランナーを実行してみます
Yes.
はい
Straight line. Cool.
直線いいですね
But we're seeing a bunch of red flags popping up. Right?
しかし 赤色の警告がいくつか表示されますねわかりますか?
It's alright. We ran through a tree.
大丈夫 木は通り抜けちゃうからね 大丈夫
Okay, first of all,
OK 最初に
we're going from zero miles per hour instantly to about 50.
車は時速 0 マイルから一瞬で 50 マイルになりました
That's going to create a lot of jerk.
たくさんのジャークを作り出しています
Right. Okay, so, what do we do next?
そうですねOK では次はどうしますか?
Well, now we can actually try to,
そうですね 車線から外れないように走るというのは?
maybe, either stay in our lane.That would be nice.
いいと思いませんか?
Staying in the lane is nice.
車線から外れない いいですね
So let's see, could we use Frenet coordinates for that?
では見てみましょう Frenet 座標を使用してみるというのは?
Sure.
いいですね
So, let's see, we've got, we're creating this.
今はこんな状態ですね
We have this concept list of 50 points.
コンセプトリストは 50 ポイントになっています
In this list of 50 points.
このリストは 50 ポイントになっていますね
But these are x, y coordinates.
しかし これは x, y 座標です
And what if instead we're using s, d coordinates?
代わりに s, d 座標を使うというのはどうですか?
Okay, so, let's try and push
OK やってみましょう
new_x_y coordinates onto the vectors
新しい xy 座標をベクターにプッシュして
that keep us in our way instead of just driving us straight off the road.
車線から外れないように走行させます
Right. If we want to try to stay in the lanes Frenet is going to be very helpful to us.
そうですね車線を外れないよう走行させる場合に Frenet は非常に便利です
Got it. So we could have something like double next_s and that's going to be like get.
了解こんな感じかな double next_s それから get で
Or double, sorry.
あるいは double ごめん
We could start with the cars_s.
cars_s で開始できますよ
Okay. Got it.
OK了解
So, we would do double getXY.
では double getXY
We'll use getXY a little bit after the next test.
getXY はもう少しあとで使います
Got it.
了解
getXY will be actually using our next_s, next_d.
getXY は実際 next_s next_d を使用します
Got it. So, we'll do something like car_s+i*dist_inc.
了解では car_s+i*dist_inc
So, the car_s got a certain,
car_s で特定の
s coordinate and Frenet coordinates.
s 座標と Frenet 座標を得ます
And as we iterate through this loop,
そして このループを繰り返して
we want to step forward another dist_inc each time. Is that right?
毎回 別の dist_inc に進んでいきますそうですよね?
Yes, except for instead of just i1 do i+1.
はい ただし i だけではなく i+1 にしてください
Why is that?
どうしてですか?
Otherwise, our first point will be exactly where the car is at,
i+1 にしないと 最初のポイントが現在の車の位置になるので
and it won't be transitioning.
遷移していきません
Got it.
了解
And it'll be sitting still.
停止したままになってしまうんですね
Got it. So, we could do i+1.
了解i+1 にします
Got it. Okay.
OK
Yes. Now, what do you think about next_d?
そうですねnext_d はどうしますか?
So, double next_d, next_d.
double next_d
We are in the middle lane,
私の記憶が正しければ
if I remember right.
真ん中の車線にいましたよね
And, the waypoints are measured from the double yellow line in the middle of the road.
ウェイポイントは道路中央の黄色い二重線から測定されます
So, we are like one and a half lanes from where the waypoints are?
とすると ウェイポイントから 1.5 車線のあたりにいるということですね?
Yes, that's right.
はい そのとおりです
And I think I read in the classroom that the lanes are four meters wide.
クラスルームで車線の幅は 4 メートルと読み上げたと思います
So, for one and a half lanes away from where the waypoints are,
ですから ウェイポイントから 1.5 車線ということは
one and a half times four meters wide is six.
1.5 x 4 メートル = 6 になります
Yes.
はい
So, I'll just set that to six.
では 6 を設定しますね
Yes, that's what's really helpful about Frenet,
はい この数値が非常に役に立ちます
is if we just want to stay in this constant lane or the d_cons as well.
一定の車線 d_cons に留まらせておくことができます
Got it. Okay.
わかりましたOK
Now we're actually ready to create our vector of x, y.
これで x, y のベクターを作成する準備ができました
Got it.
了解
So getXY function will help us with that.
getXY 関数がここで役に立ちます
So it may be a vector.
ベクターですね
Yes, let's go back and look at that,
はい 戻ってちょっと見てみます
I kind of forgot what the signature of vector getXY function is.
ベクター getXY 関数のシグネチャ―を忘れてしまいました
Sure.
大丈夫ですよ
So if we scroll way,
上へ 上へスクロール
way up and we look at getXY.
していき getXY を見つけます
So, it takes s,
getXY は s
d, it takes maps_s,
d をとり maps_s
maps_x, maps_y and it passes back a vector of doubles.
maps_x maps_y をとって ベクター double に渡すのですね
Yes, and we've seen that just two doubles.
はい その 2 つの double を見ました
Yes, just your X and Y.
はい X と Y です
One X, one Y. Okay.
X が 1 つ Y が 1 つですね OK
So, let's do that.
では やってみましょう
So, we'll have maybe,
ですから vector&amp;lt;double&amp;gt;
vector&amp;lt;double&amp;gt; xy = getXY and that's
xy = getXY
going to be next_s, next_d, maps_s, maps.
(next_s, next_d, maps_s, maps_
Of course, it'll be called something all the different than maps_s.
当然 すべて違うものを呼び出すので maps_s ではないですよね
You're so tricky.
トリッキーですね
Yes. That was an abbreviation.
はい短縮形でしたね
So, right there, map_waypoints_s.
そこにあります map_waypoints_s
Let's see.
どこだろう
Line 195.
195 行目
Just going to look for where you declared it.
宣言したところを見ています
So you declared map_waypoints_x,
map_waypoints_x
map_waypoints_y and maps_waypoints_s. Okay.
map_waypoints_y と maps_waypoints_s と宣言していますOK
The function was using an abbreviated handle.
関数は短縮ハンドルを使用していました
Got it. So, map_waypoints_s,
了解map_waypoints_s
map_waypoints_x, map_waypoints_y.
map_waypoints_x map_waypoints_y
Okay, so now I've got X and Y.
OK これで X と Y がわかりました
Cool.
素晴らしい
And if I just push them on here, so, next_x_vals,
ここでプッシュします next_x_vals は
just going to be the first element in x y and then we'll push
xy の 1 番目の要素になり next y_vals が
the second element in x y onto the y vector to the next y_vals vector.
2 番目の要素になります
(xy[1]).
(xy[1])
Yes.
はい
So, we'll save that.
これを保存します
So far so good.
ここまでは問題ありませんね
See, I think it's going to make.
次は make ですよね
The suspense is killing me.
ああ ドキドキします
All right. Path planning.
OKpath_planning
Yep, let's see how it runs.
よし 実行してみましょう
Let's do it.
やってみましょう
We expect it to stay in its lane this time.
今回は車線内で走行してくれることを期待しています
It's staying in its lane.
車線内を走行しています
It's still on the red but it is staying in its lane.
まだ赤い表示は出ますが 車線内を走行しています
Yes, so let's kind of talk about what's happening.
はい そうなんです 何が起きているのか説明しますね
So, it didn't take too many lines of code just to get to stay in its lane,
車線内に留まらせるためだけにコードを書いたので それほど行数は多くありませんでしたが
but it's a very crude representation of these points.
ポイントの表示がかなり雑です
We're relying quite a bit on
getXY 関数にかなり依存しているので
the get_xy function and it works pretty well except on these boundary cases.
境界の問題以外はうまく動いています
Our map is made up of these sparse waypoints and we have these corners and line segments.
地図は少量のウェイポイントで構成されているため こうしたコーナーや線分ができます
At these corners, these points tend to get kind of bunched
こうしたコーナーでは ポイントが集まって
up and that's going to cause some acceleration and jerk issues.
加速とジャークの原因になります
Got it. It looks like we're violating the speed limit.
わかりました制限速度を違反しているようです
The speed limit's 55 miles an hour and we're-
これは 制限速度が時速 55 マイルなのに 私たちは
That's because we're still using 0.5.
まだ 0.5 を使っているためです
We could fix that maybe by doing 0.4 but-
0.4 にすれば修正できますが
Let's start with that and see what happens.
それを試してみましょう
We're really harassing the other cars on the road as well.
どうやら他の車にかなり嫌がらせをしているみたいですしね
You're not a good driver.
運転はうまくないみたいですね
Okay, so let's take a look at,
OK では見ていきましょう
so if we just shorten distance increment to something like 0.3,
距離の増分を 0.3 あたりに短くしたら
is that going to solve our speed limit problems?
制限速度違反の問題を解決できますか?
It will help the average speed.
平均速度の役に立つでしょう
It should be much lower,
かなり低くすべきですが
but there'll still be times and those
まだ時間もありますし コーナーの問題もあります
corner cases where the points may get bunched up and
コーナーではポイントが集まって
their spacing is a little weird just in
その転換時に間隔が少しおかしくなります
that transformation because it's not exactly linear.
これは正確には直線ではないためです
Got it. So, the average speed is a lot lower,
わかりました平均速度がかなり遅くなりました
we're at 33 miles an hour now.
現在 時速 33 マイルで走行しています
Yes.
はい
And we're not violating the speed limit that often,
また それほど頻繁に制限速度を違反しているわけでもないのに
but every once in a while, it does say we are violating the speed limit.
ときどき 制限速度を違反していると警告されます
Yes and we can kind of visually see that on those corner cases.
はい 警告はコーナーのときに見えます
It looks like the points are, for the most part,
ポイントは ほとんどの部分で
all nicely spaced except there's this edge.
このエッジを除いて すべてうまく間隔をとっているようです
Got it. So now we've got the car driving slowly in its lane,
了解つまり 車は車線内をゆっくり走行しているのに
but there are this kind of inflection points where all of a sudden the car jerks,
屈折か所があって その屈折か所で突然 ジャークになり
maybe even violates the speed limit.
また 制限速度違反も起こしてしまうということですね
What we really need to do is smooth out that path.
ここで必要なことはパスを滑らかにすることです
We need to smooth the path.
パスを滑らかにする必要がある
So, how are we going to do that?
トラジェクトリーを生成するレッスンにおいて、ジャークを最小化するレッスンを行いました。
There was a lesson on jerk minimization in the trajectory generation lesson.
角度が 近いけれど現在の地点より後ろにあるウェイポイントではなく
But I saw it in the classroom,
しかし それはクラスルームで見ました
you mentioned something about splines.
スプラインについて触れていましたよね
There's this awesome spline library that we
スプラインライブラリという素晴らしいライブラリがあり
can take advantage of and it's not too far-fetched
その利点を利用することができます
from what we're doing in previous projects like MPC where
ウェイポイントに合う多項式を使用する MPC など 前回のプロジェクトで行ったことと
we're using a polynomial that fit through waypoints.
それほどかけ離れているわけではありません
Okay.
OK
There's some advantages of a spline over
スプラインには多項式に勝る利点があります
a polynomial where the spline is guaranteed to go through
スプラインを使用すると必ずすべてのポイントを通過します
all the points because it's a piecewise function of polynomials.
多項式の関数の方が手間がかかります
Got it. So, here's the spline library in the classroom.
了解これがクラスルームのスプラインライブラリです
So I remember in college,
大学時代
I took a whole class on numerical analysis,
数値解析の全クラスをとったのを憶えています
and my memory is like a third of the class was on splines.
私の記憶では その 3 分の 1 がスプラインについてでした
Okay.
そうだったんですね
There are all sorts of weird ways to calculate splines,
スプラインを計算する変な方法があって
piecewise functions that go through points.
ポイントを通過する区分的関数で計算するんですよね
They're kind of like polynomial fits,
多項式フィッティングのようなものだけれど
except they go through all the points and they're
すべてのポイントを通過するという点と
guaranteed to have smooth transitions through the points.
滑らかなポイント遷移が確実に得られるという点が多項式フィッティングと異なるんですよね
Yes, first and second derivatives.
そうです 第 1 および第 2 微分係数です
Right. Why use splines instead of polynomial fits?
そうですねなぜ 多項式フィッティングではなくスプラインを使うのですか?
Because we have this library here that will make it very easy for us.
ライブラリがここに用意されているため 私たちとって非常に楽なんですね
Got it. So somebody wrote the code,
了解誰かがコードを書いたので
so we're going to use splines instead of polynomial fit.
多項式フィッティングではなくスプラインを使用するということですね
Single header file.
シングルヘッダーファイルです
To single header file.
シングルヘッダーファイル
Okay. So we've got this header file here, we'll download it.
OKここにヘッダーファイルがあります これをダウンロードします
I think I've actually already done that.
たしか 既にダウンロードしたと思います
Let's take a look in our source file.
ソースファイルを見てみましょう
Source, spline.
ソース スプライン
Yep, it's already there.
ありました
So if we come over here,
ここまできたら
we'll have to add it way up top in our includes list.
コードの上の方の include リストにスプラインを追加する必要があります
Yes, include spline.h.
そうです include spline.h です
Got it.
了解
But you could do a polynomial fitting here too.
けれど 多項式フィッティングを使用することもできるんですよ
There's a lot of freedom when it comes to building this path planner.
パスプランナーを構築する場合はかなり自由なんです
Okay. But I like code that someone else wrote for me.
OKでも 私は誰かが自分のために書いてくれたコードがいいです
Yes, it's kind of nice.
はい 親切ですよね
Let's see. Do we have spines.h in here anywhere?
では見てみることにしますspines.h がここのどこかにありますか?
No, you'll need to include it.
ありません インクルードする必要があります
Okay, #include.
OK #include
Do you remember if it's spline.h or splines.h?
spline.h だったか splines.h だったか覚えていますか?
I think it's just spline.h, I would say.
spline.h だったと思います
Spline.h, okay. I shouldn't have cleared my bash history here,
Spline.h OKbash 履歴を消さなければよかった
ll_source_spline.h Okay, so now we've included spline.h,
ll_source_spline.h OK これで spline.h をインクルードしました
and what we need to use spline.h for is
spline.h の使用目的は シミュレーターで車が走行する
smoothing out that kind of disjointed path that the car was following in the simulator.
ガタガタしたパスを滑らかにすることです
Yes. I really like your solution,
はいとても良いソリューションだと思うのですが
but I might try to do something a little bit different.
私だったら少し違う方法を試してみます
What are you trying to do?
何を試すのですか?
Well, I might actually try to create some points,
ポイントを作ろうと思います
just a couple, that are pretty far spaced,
2 つか 3 つだけで 間隔をかなり広くとります
maybe 30 meters or so,
おそらく 30 メートルくらいかな
and then use a spline to fit that
次にスプラインを使ってフィットさせて
and then actually try to take points inside that spline.
そのスプラインの中にポイントを入れます
Got it.
了解
Okay. So let's try that.
OKでは やってみましょう
Okay. I just so happen to send you some code that does that.
OKこれを行うコードを送っておきましたよ
Oh, my goodness. Okay. Let's switch to your file.
え そうなんですかOKそちらのファイルに切り替えます
I think I saved that in the source directory, aaron.cpp.
確かソースディレクトリの aaron.cpp に保存したと思います
I don't know why I tried the cd, source aaron.cpp.
なんで cd しようとしちゃったんだろう cp ../src/aaron.cpp
Now, we'll copy that over to main.
コードを main にコピーします
So now you've got this main cpp file.
これで main.cpp ファイルにコードがコピーされました
I've already got spline.h included in everything.
spline.h も既にすべてに含ませています
Okay. You're way ahead of me.
OKずいぶん 先に行っていますね
Okay. So, let's scroll down
OKスクロールダウンしていきます
here and then maybe you can kind of walk us through what's going on.
どのようになっているのか説明してもらえますか
Yes, definitely.
はい もちろんです
...to do or we can just search to do.
...TODO はどこかな 検索してみましょう
We're almost there, int main
もうすぐです int main まできたから
Almost there.
あと少し
We're very close.
もうそこです
Okay. We're doing what we're doing last time and collecting all those map waypoints.
OK最後に行っていたこと行い すべての地図のウェイポイントを収集しています
Let's see.
見てみましょう
So if telemetry,
if telemetry があって
then you've got some commented code here.
一部 コードがコメントされています
Yeah, we'll kind of go through that later.
はい これについては後で説明します
Okay.
OK
All right, we'll keep things as simple as possible for right now.
では ここではできるだけシンプルにしていきます
All we want the car to do is stay in its lane and go at
車線内を走行すること
a constant velocity and try to be as smooth.
一定の速度で走行すること 滑らかに走行することがここでの目的です
Okay.
OK
Not violate its acceleration and jerk.
速度制限およびジャーク制限に違反しないこと
Got it. So what are you doing here?
了解ここでは 何を行っているのですか?
Well, to start out with,
まず初めに
I'm going to actually come up here and define two variables.
ここで 2 つの変数を指定します
Okay.
OK
These two variables are my lane.
2 つの変数は車線です
So I'm going to start in lane one.
車線 1 から始めます
I can use this so I can quickly switch to other lanes if I need to.
これを使うと必要な時に素早く別の車線に切り替えることができます
So lane zero is kind of the far left lane,
車線 0 は左端の車線です
lane one is the middle lane, and lane two is the right lane?
車線 1 は真ん中の車線 車線 2 は右端の車線ですね?
Yes, exactly. And then,
はい そのとおりです次に
I'm also going to be telling it some reference velocity.
参照速度を伝えます
Right here, I just kind of want to go as close to the speed limit as possible.
ここでは できるだけ制限速度に近い速度で走行させようと思っています
I don't want to go over it, so I'm doing 49.5.
制限速度は超えないようにしたいので 49.5 にします
Okay.
OK
And once I come in here and I get past just getting some of these variables,
ここから先の変数は少し飛ばして
I'm going to be setting this previous size,
prev_size を設定します
which comes from the previous path size.
このサイズは前のパスサイズです
So I had this previous list of
この前のポイントリストを使用します
points and that can really help me when I'm doing a transition.
変更する場合に非常に便利です
So this is the last path that the car was following
これは車が追いかけていた最後のパスですね?
before it does this particular run through of calculating more points?
このあと さらにポイントを計算し これらを行うわけですね
Yes. And the simulator will actually be telling me what that previous path was.
そうです実際にはシミュレーターで前のパスの情報が提示されます
Got it. Okay.
OK
So, let's kind of scroll down here.
では スクロールダウンします
So will that be 50 because the path is always 50 points?
パスは常に50 ポイントだから 50 になりますか?
You could even do 100, you could do 1,000.
100 でもできますし 1,000 でもできますよ
You have a lot of freedom to have this path planner do as many points ahead as you want.
パスプランナーでは好きなだけ自由にポイントを設けることができます
Got it.
了解
And there are some advantages and disadvantages to doing that.
これには長所と短所があります
Okay.
OK
If it gets stuck at 1,000 and you're using previous points,
1,000 で行き詰った場合に前のポイントを使用していると
maybe there's some sudden change in
環境に突然の変更が発生し
the environment and it wouldn't be able to react in
時間内に反応できなくなる可能性があります
time because it's stuck using those previous points.
前のポイントで引っかかってしまうためです
Okay.
OK
So I was kind of saying that I kind of want to use these sparsely spaced waypoints.
ウェイポイントの間隔をかなりとって配置すると言ったのはこのためです
So I'm just going to create this vector double list and kind of build from there.
ですから ベクター double のリストを作って そこからビルドしようと思います
Also I want to keep track of my reference state.
また リファレンスの状態を追跡しようと思います
It's either going to be where the car is at or it's going
車の現在位置か この前のパスのエンドポイント
to be at this previous path's endpoint.
のいずれかになります
So I defined this reference x, y and yaw.
このリファレンス x y yaw を定義しました
So x, y and angle.
x y と角度ですね
Now I'm just going to check out what the previous path size was.
前のパスサイズを確認します
It's either going to be pretty close to
かなり空に近いか
empty or it's going to have some points that I can take advantage of.
利用できるポイントがあるかのいずれかです
If it's pretty much empty,
空に近い場合は
I'm just going to use a car state.
車の状態を使用します
So right here, I'm interested in
ここに 車の角度に対してタンジェントとなる
creating this path that's tangent to the angle of the car.
このパスを作ろうかと思っています
So I'm going to be looking at where the car is at,
車の位置を探し
and I can just kind of go backwards in time based on
角度に基づいて時間を戻り
its angle and I can generate two points to make sure that path is tangent.
ポイントを 2 つ生成してそのパスがタンジェントとなるようにします
So that's if I'm just starting out and I don't really have any previous path points.
開始したばかりで前のパスポイントがない場合はこうなります
If I do have some previous path points,
前のパスポイントがある場合は
I'm just going to be doing the same thing where I'm going to make sure it's tangent by
それが必ずタンジェントとなるよう その前のパスの最後のポイントと
using the last point in that previous path and its second last point.
最後から 2 番目のポイントを使用して同じことを行います
And I'm just going to be adding this to my points x and points y.
これをポイント x とポイント y に追加します
I'm also going to change this reference x and reference y to
また このリファレンス x とリファレンス y を
the last element in the previous path and then go ahead and
前のパスの最後の要素に変更して
calculate it just using our tangent.
タンジェントを使って計算します
Got it.
了解
So basically what you're doing is you're looking at what were
基本的に何をしているかというと 車が追いかけていた
the last couple of points in the previous path that the car was following,
前のパスの最後のいくつかのポイントに注目し
and then calculating what angle the car was heading in using those last couple of points.
そのポイントを使って車の進行方向の角度を計算しているんですよね
Yeah.
はい
Is that right? And then you're pushing them onto a list of previous points?
そうですよね?次に前のポイントのリストにそれをプッシュしているんですよね
Yeah. So, so far I've pushed two x and two y.
はい そのとおりですこれまでのところ x を 2 つと y を 2 つプッシュしました
Got it. So you've got two points basically on this pair of vectors?
了解では 基本的にはこのベクターの組み合わせには 2 つのポイントがあるのですね?
Yes.
はい
And now that's my starting reference.
そして これが開始レファレンスです
And then here's some other points.
これが他のポイントです
So I'm using Frenet.
Frenet を使用しています
This is kind of what you were doing before,
前回 行ったことですが
but I'm just making sure that they are spaced pretty far apart.
今回はポイントの間隔をかなり広くとっています
Got it. So instead of just looking at one distance increment,
了解ひとつの距離増分ではなく
you're looking out basically 30, 60, 90.
30 60 90 にしているんですね
And instead of looping through and creating 50
また ループして 50 ポイント作るのではなく
of these you're just creating three of them?
3 ポイントだけ作っているのですね
That's right.
そうです
Okay.
OK
So I'm going to be pushing three more points but instead of
あと 3 ポイント プッシュするのですが
just them being 0.5 meter spaced,
間隔を 0.5 メートルではなく
they're all the way to 30.
30 メートルにしようと思います
Got it. And where I had six as the d coordinate you have two plus four times lane,
了解私は d 座標に 6 を設定しましたが あなたのコードでは 2+4*lane になっています
lane here is one.
ここの車線は 1 だから
So two plus four times one is going to be six.
2+4*1 は 6 になるわけですね
Yeah.
はい
But if you ever change the lane variable that would get to [inaudible].
ただし lane の変数を変更すると走行車線も変わるのですね
That can be very helpful too.
非常に便利です
Got it. Okay.
OK
Yeah. So go ahead and push those points.
はいでは これらのポイントをプッシュします
So what is this? What are these vectors of points have now?
これは何ですか?このベクターのポイントは何になりますか?
They have the two previous points plus they
前の 2 ポイント足す
have the location of the car in 30 meters basically and then in 60 and 90 meters?
30 メートルの位置 次に 60 メートル 90 メートルになるのですね?
Yes.
はい
So it's got five points on it now, right?
つまり 今回は 5 ポイントになるのですね?
Right.
そのとおりです
Okay.
OK
Okay. Now this is something that's actually very helpful to do that I found,
OKこれは実際 非常に便利なことがわかりました
and that's doing a transformation to this local car's coordinates.
このローカルの車の座標への変換を行ってくれます
So something that we did at MPC.
MPC でやったことと同じようなものです
We shift it so we make sure that the car or
それをシフトして 車または
that last point of the previous path is at zero,
前のパスの最後のポイントが 0, 0 の起点に
zero, the origin and its angles at zero degrees.
その角度がゼロ度になるようにします
And this will come into play later.
これはあとで登場します
So just bear with me maybe.
もう少し待ってください
Bear with you, okay.
もう少し待ちます OK
So we're taking if the car is heading this way,
車がこの方向へ進んでいる場合
kind of an xy coordinates,
xy 座標の方向ですね
we want to shift this so we're looking in the car's reference frame.
これをシフトさせる つまり車のリファレンスフレームを参照するんですね
So it's just kind of going straight ahead instead of being at
45 度ではなく直進する
45 degrees maybe it should always be at zero degrees.
常に 0 度にしておくということですね
Makes the math much easier to work with.
計算が簡単になります
Makes the math easier. Okay.
計算が簡単になるんですねOK
Okay. So we do that transformation here.
OKでは ここでその変換を行います
It's a shift in rotation.
回転のシフトです
Okay.
OK
So this is some of the math you might recognize from MPC.
MPC で見たような数学です
Here is that spline that we've been building up to.
これは私たちが構築していたスプラインです
Back to the spline, okay.
spline に戻るんですね OK
Yeah. So I define a spline s and then I
はいスプラインを定義して
simply set some points x and points y to the spline.
ポイント x とポイント y をスプラインに設定します
Okay.
OK
And here is actually
そしてここで
where I'm building what we were working with last time xx vowels and xy vowels.
前回 作業していた next_x_vals と next_y_vals をビルドしています
These are actual points that the path planner is going to be using.
これがパスプランナーが使用する実際のポイントです
Okay. So we have this one set of x and y points and now we've got
OKこの x ポイントと y ポイントのセットを 1 つ設定しました
this other set that's empty at the moment that we need to build the future path in.
もう 1 セットあり そちらは現時点では空白で将来のパスをそこにビルドする必要があるわけですね
Yes. So we're just getting that all set up.
はいこれをすべて設定します
We've been talking a lot about the previous path and here's where it comes into play.
前のパスについていろいろと話しましたが ここでそれが登場します
Okay.
OK
So if I have any points from my previous path I'm just
前のパスからのポイントがある場合は
going to go ahead and I'm going to add them to my path planner.
そのポイントをそのままパスプランナーに追加します
Got it.
了解
This kind of helps out with the transition.
これは遷移の際 役に立ちます
So you make sure that instead of recreating the path from scratch every single time,
毎回 ゼロからパスを再作成するのではなく
why not just add points onto it and work with what you still had left from last time.
ポイントを追加して 残っているものを再利用することができます
Got it. So if the previous path was
了解では 前のパスが 50 ポイントなら
50 points then there are always going to be 50 points here that we had on?
常に 50 ポイントになるわけですね?
Yeah. That's what we're kind of doing right
はいそのとおりです
here where we have 50 minus a previous path x dot size.
50-previous_path_x.size です
Got it. Isn't this 50 minus previous path x dot size always going to be zero,
了解この 50-previous_path_x.size は常に 0 になるとは限らないのですか?
it's previous path x dot size is 50?
previous_path_x.size は 50 ですか?
Previous path size will be less than 50.
前のパスサイズは 50 より少なくなります
Let's say that you're running an iteration,
反復を実行しているとして
you generate 50 points.
50 ポイントを生成します
Maybe the simulator goes through three of those points.
おそらくシミュレーターはその 3 ポイントを走行します
So you have 47 left over that it's going to report the next time around.
ですから 47 ポイント残っていて それが次回 報告されます
So now you have 47.
だから 47 ポイント
The previous path x dot or previous path x is not the full previous path,
previous_path_x. または previous_path_x はフルパスではなく
it's whatever kind of
パックマンのナゲットのように
pac-man nuggets in the previous path didn't get eaten up by the car.
車がすべてのポイントを消費してしまうわけではないんですね
Yeah, exactly.
はい そのとおりです
So if the car ate up three points out of 50 point path last time,
車が前回 50 ポイントのうち 3 ポイントを消費したとすると
the previous path is going to have the 47 remaining points.
前のパスには 47 ポイントが残っているわけですね
So we only need to generate three points.
だから 生成する必要があるのは 3 ポイントだけなんですね
Got it. Or if the car ate up 40 points previous path will have 10 points left.
了解また 車が 40 ポイント消費したとしたら 前のパスには 10ポイント残るということですね
Exactly.
そのとおりです
Got it. Okay.
OK
All right.
わかりました
So we add on our previous path points.
前のパスのポイントを足します
And here's where it gets a little bit interesting.
ここから 少し面白くなってきます
I went ahead and I added these points to the spline but I
このポイントをスプラインに追加しましたが
want to figure out how to space
このポイントをスプラインに沿って
these points along the spline so that I go at my desired speed.
配置する間隔を計算し 目的の速度にしたいわけです
Wait, where did you add them to the spline?
ちょっと待ってください どこに追加したんですか?
So they're all added right here.
ここですべて追加されています
I added points x and points y to s.
ptsx と ptsy を s に追加しました
Got it. So these are those five anchor points not the previous path point.
了解では これらは 5 アンカーポイントであって 前のパスのポイントではないのですね
Exactly, we're dealing with kind of two sets.
そのとおりです ここでは 2 セットを処理しています
Okay.
OK
If you will. We're dealing with our far-spaced waypoints that make up the spline,
同様にするのであれば スプラインを構成するウェイポイントの間隔を広く配置し
and we deal with our path planning points.
そしてパスプランニングのポイントを処理します
Okay. Let's call the first set like the anchor points so I can keep them straight.
OK1つ目のセットはわかりやすいようアンカーポイントと呼びますね
And then the second set will be like the next x files or future path or something.
そして 2 つ目のセットは next x ファイルまたは未来のパスと呼びますね
Yeah.
はい
Okay. So you've added the anchor points to the spline,
OKこの真ん中あたりでアンカーポイントを
kind of in the middle here.
スプラインに追加したのですね
You loaded up the future path with whatever was left of the previous path.
そして未来のパスを前のパスの残りと一緒に読み込んでいます
Exactly.
そのとおりです
So there's some continuity, I guess.
だから連続性が生じるわけですね
And now we're back to looking at the spline and the anchor points. Is that right?
そして ここでスプラインとアンカーポイントに戻ってくるわけですね これで正しいですか？
Yes.
はい
Okay.
OK
And this would be a great time to bring up some visual aid.
このあたりで視覚資料を見てみます
Okay. Bring up some visual aid.
OK視覚資料を見てみましょう
Yes.
はい
Let's see, like that visual aid?
これがそうですか?
Exactly.
そうです
Okay. That's beautiful. Did you do that?
OKすごいですね自分で作ったんですか?
Oh yeah. True artist over here.
もちろんです本物のアーティストだな
Here is our car in our local coordinate system.
これがローカル座標系内の車です
Okay.
OK
And you can see it's going at zero degrees.
見てわかるように 0 度です
This is kind of our spline that we have.
これはスプラインです
Okay.
OK
What I would love to get is these points that are spaced along
ここでしたいことは これらのポイントをスプラインに沿って
the spline and spaced in the way that the car will go at the desired speed.
配置する しかも車が目的の速度で走行する間隔で配置したいわけです
Got it. So you need these points to be kind of
了解つまり 車が時速 50 マイルあるいは
the exact right distance aparts if the car is going
49.5 マイルで走行する場合
50 miles an hour or 49.5 miles an hour or whatever?
ポイントを正確に正しい距離間隔で配置する必要があるわけですね
Right.
そうです
Got it. Can't you just look that up?
了解どこかに参照できる数値があるんですか?
So I have to do some math.
計算しないといけません
Okay. I'm just going to linearize and actually,
OK線形化すると
it ends up working pretty well.
うまくいきました
Okay.
OK
I'm just going to do that by looking out some horizon value,
水平値を見つけます
let's say 30 meters.
30 メートルとしましょう
Okay.
OK
And we can figure out where that point lies on the spline
これでスプラインにポイントを配置する場所を計算できます
because we have this s function and it's just f of x.
この s 関数があり この関数は x のうちの f だからです
We give our spline some x and it will give us some y.
スプラインに x を与えると y が得られます
And we just calculate the distance from the car to this target point that I'm setting.
車から設定している目的のポイントまでの距離を計算します
We have this d. Here's where the math comes in.
これが d で これが計算です
Okay.
OK
I want to split this up into n pieces.
これを n 個のピースに分けたいと思います
And it turns out that these n pieces times
ですから n ピース x 0.02 に
0.02 because the car will visit a point every 0.02 seconds.
なります 車は各ポイントまでそれぞれ 0.02 秒かけて走行します
Okay.
OK
Times the velocity, this is actually my desired velocity,
これに目的の速度をかけると
is equal to D.
d になります
Okay. Okay.
OKOK
That's because this is in seconds.
これが秒単位であるのに対し
This is in meters per second.
こちらは秒あたりのメートル単位です
This cancels out the seconds, we have meters.
これが 2 番目を打ち消すのでメートルになります
In each end piece there's some meters.
ピースを通過するごとメートル数が出ます
And when we have all the ends,
すべてのピースに到達すると
we get the full distance.
全距離が得られます
Got it. So that's velocity right there.
了解それが速度になるのですね
That is.
そうです
I couldn't quite tell what that was. Okay. That's a vel for velocity?
最初 なんて書いてあるのかよくわからなかったのですが OKvelocity (速度) の vel なんですね?
All right. So, what's the takeaway here?
わかりましたここで覚えておくべき点は何ですか?
The takeaway is that when we do this,
これを行うとき
we can calculate what n should be.
n を計算することができます
And since this is just a triangle, it turns out that,
これは単純な三角形で
since this is broken up into n for the hypotenuse,
その斜辺を n 個に分割するため
will also be broken up an n for this x axis as well.
x 軸も n 個に分割されます
Okay.
OK
And then, once we have these x values,
この x 値がわかれば
we just tell the spline, "Hey,
スプラインに「この x の y 値は
what's the y value for this x?"
何になる?」と聞けばいいわけです
And we get these points.
するとポイント数が得られます
So you just tell the spline,
スプラインに
"Here's an x value,
「これが x 値だよ
can you give us the corresponding y value for this x value?"
これに該当する y 値を教えて?」と聞くんですね
Exactly.
そのとおりです
Got it.
了解
And we just go through that for how many points we
これを行って必要なポイント数を得て
need and we get XYs along the spline.
スプラインに沿った XY を得ます
Got it. Can you show that in the code?
了解コードで見せてもらえますか?
Yes, definitely.
はい もちろんです
Okay.
OK
So that's exactly what we're doing right here.
これです
That's our horizon going out 30.
水平値 30 はここです
Got it. There we go. Sorry.
了解ここですね失礼
Okay.
OK
Our target y like I was saying,
話していた目的つまりターゲット
we just ask the spline what's the y for that given x.
スプラインにこの x 値に対する y 値を聞いています
Aaron, this is a vm, you don't use the mouse.
アーロン これは vim なのでマウスは使いません
Very true. And then,
そのとおり次に
we have this target distance.
ターゲットの距離を得ます
And that is just simply doing this distance calculation
前のパスの最後のポイント
from the car whether it be the last point
または車自体からターゲットまでの
in the previous path or the car itself to that target.
距離を計算するだけです
Okay.
OK
We had this x add-on which starts at zero.
x_add_on これはゼロで開始します
And this has to do with two of that local transformation that we did.
これは 以前に行った 2 つのローカル遷移で行う必要があります
We started at the origin.
起点から開始していました
Got it. Okay. So here,
OKここ
target x is 30 and then we're getting the y value by simply,
target_x は 30 で y 値を得ます
we've declared the spline and now all we have to do is pass target x
スプラインは宣言したので ここですべきことは target_x を
into the spline s. So up here we declare the spline,
スプライン s に渡すだけです 上の方でスプラインを宣言していますね
here we set the anchor points.
どの様にすればいいですか?
And now all we have to do is pass in 30 to s and we get back the y value.
つまり 30 を s に渡すと y 値が得られます
Pretty easy to use this spline library.
このスプラインライブラリの使い方は非常に簡単ですよね
I love when people write easy code.
誰かが簡単なコードを書いてくれるのがいいな
So now we're just adding on those points that are along the spline.
スプラインに沿ってポイントを追加していきます
Okay.
OK
This is the math that I was showing in that previous slide.
前のスライドでお見せした計算です
I'm trying to figure out what n should be.
n の数を計算しています
I have that target distance,
これがターゲットの距離
so I have this reference velocity.
これがリファレンス速度です
I'm dividing it by 2.24 because I was saying this was in miles per hour,
2.24 で割っています これは1 時間当たりのマイル数だとお伝えしたと思いますが
it needs to be in meters per second.
1 秒あたりのメートル数にしなければならないためです
And then, I have this x point.
次にこの x ポイントを得ます
And that's just going to be whatever the x add-on was
x_add_on+(target_x)/N
before plus this target x divided by n.
です
Okay. So n is what you showed us in the diagram.
OK Nは図で見せてくれたものですね
And now, x point is each of those little hash marks on the-
x ポイントは視覚資料で見た x 軸上の
On the x axis of that visual.
小さなハッシュマークですね
On the x axis of that visual. Okay. So x add-on is kind of where we start.
視覚資料の x 軸です  OK  x_add_on は開始点で
It's going to be zero,
ゼロになります
and then we're adding on our target x divided by n which is the number of hash marks.
target_x を足して N で割っています これがハッシュマークの数です
Yes.
はい
Got it. Okay. And then,
了解　OK　次に
to get the y point just ask the s what the y point is from the x point.
y ポイントを得るため x ポイントで得られる y ポイントを聞いています
Got it. And so that tells us on the spline where is
了解これで スプラインでの各ウェイポイント
each little pearl or pac-man nugget or waypoint actually,
パール状のパックマンのナゲットみたいなやつの位置を指示し
such that they are far enough apart that the car goes the right speed.
また車が適切な速度で走行するよう十分な間隔をあけて配置するよう指示しているのですね
Yes.
はい
Got it. Okay. All right.
OKわかりました
And in our case we want to try to do at 49.5 miles per hour.
そして ここでは時速 49.5 マイルで走行させたいと思います
Got it.
了解
So we loop through that.
このため ループさせます
Last thing that we need to remember to do is we're in local coordinates.
最後に忘れずに行わなければならないことがあります 今 ローカル座標にいるですが
Okay.
OK
We need to go back to the global coordinates.
グローバル座標に戻さなければなりません
So like the basis transformation.
基底変換のようなものですね
Yes. So we just do the inverse of what we were doing before.
はい以前に行ったことの逆を行います
So we're doing a shift right here and then a rotation.
つまり ここでシフトしてから回転します
Got it. Okay.
OK
And then, finally, we just push that back to our next x vals and
そして 最後に これを next_x_vals と
x y vals and we're done.
next_y_vals にプッシュバックして完了です
Man, you think it will drive better than my car? It's a lot of work.
やりましたね 前よりいい走りになると思いますか?かなり作業が多かったですよね
Yes, let's try it out.
そうですね やってみましょう
Okay.
OK
And hopefully,
たしか
that one was saved and-
保存したよな
Did I forget to save it?
あれ 保存し忘れたかな?
I don't know.
わかりません
I guess, we'll see.
まあ やってみましょう
We'll know right away,
すぐにわかるでしょう
I guess. Hey, there we go.
たぶんほら 出てきました
There we go. All right.
出てきましたねやりました
So it is driving a little smoother.
少し滑らかになりましたね
There was that thing at the beginning about max jerk exceeded.
赤色のあれが冒頭に出てましたね 最大ジャークを超えていました
Yes because we're going from zero miles per hour to about 50.02 seconds.
はい 車は時速 0 マイルで開始 0.02 秒で約 50 マイルに達したためです
Got it. So we're going from a dead stop to 50 miles an hour like that.
了解では 絶対に 50 マイル以上は出ないようにしないといけないですね
Yes.
はい
Got it. Okay. This is not my daily commuting car.
OKこの車は私がいつも運転しているやつじゃないからね
Okay. So what's going to happen when it hits,
OKでは 衝突するとどうなりますか
is it going to hit the car, is it going to stop?
衝突しますか 衝突したら停止しますか?
Right now we're not checking if any cars are in front of us.
現在のところ 他の車両が前に出現するかはチェックしていません
So it will actually just rear-end the sky.
だから 後ろから追突します
Oh, boy. Oh, boy.
うわぁいやいや
Can we get a view?
見れますか?
Yep. There is the red flag for a collision.
はい衝突の赤字が表示されます
Okay. So we've got a few problems, we've got to solve here.
OKいくつか問題を発見したので ここで解決していきます
One is the cold start.
1 つ目はコールドスタートです
We're breaking our acceleration parameters on the cold start.
ゴールドスタートで加速パラメーターを突破しています
And the second is checking for cars in front of us.
2 つ目は前方に現れる車両のチェックです
Yes.
はい
So, how do we handle that?
では どう処理したらいいですかね?
Well, first of all,
第一に
it'd be nice not to hit the car in front of us.
前方に出現した車に追突しないというのがいいですね
Okay. All right.
OKいいですね
Let's avoid doing that if we can.
追突を避けられるかやってみましょう
Okay.
OK
So let's kind of come up here and you will remember,
これを見てください 一部のコードを
I had some code commented out.
コメントアウトしていたのを憶えていますか
Yes.
はい
Now it's going to come into play.
そのコードの出番です
I kind of forgotten about all that code you commented out.
コメントアウトされていたコードについてはすっかり忘れていました
Yes. So let's talk about sensor fusion now.
はいセンサーフュージョンについて説明します
Okay.
OK
Tell me about sensor fusion.
センサーフュージョンについてですね
Well, the simulator is reporting this kind of list of all the other cars on the road.
シミュレーターは路上の他のすべての車両を含むリストを報告します
And all these other cars have some s in d and xy, vx, vy values.
これら他の車両はすべて d, x, y, vx, vy の値に s を持っています
Okay.
OK
We really want to use that to try to figure out where cars are at,
それらを使って他の車両の位置や
how fast they are going and how we should behave as a result.
走行速度を計算し それによって私たちの車にどのような動きをさせるか計算します
Okay.
OK
So right now, if we want to avoid hitting a car in front of us,
前方に出現する車両への追突を避ける場合
we need to actually go through
このセンサーフュージョンのリストを使用して
this sensor fusion list and see if a car is in our lane or not.
私たちの車が走行している車線に他の車がいるかどうかをチェックする必要があります
And then, how close that car is to us.
次に その車との距離を計算します
Okay.
OK
And if it's too close, we do some action.
距離が近すぎる場合は何らかのアクションを起こします
So, right now, I'm just doing this to help out.
それをこれからやっていきます
I'm looking at the previous size or
前のサイズまたは前のパスサイズを
a previous path size and if I had points to work with,
見て 作業するポイントがあれば
I'm just going to change the car s. So it's actually
car_s を変更します これは
representative of the previous path laps points s.
前のパスのラップポイント s を表しています
Okay.
OK
So I'm going to be doing this in Frenet because actually,
これを Frenet で行おうと思います
it's quite easy if I work in Frenet for doing this kind of logic.
こうした論理の作業を行う場合 Frenet で作業する方が簡単です
Okay. All right, so show me.
OKわかりました では やってみせてください
Okay. So for instance,
OKたとえば
I'm going to be looking at a D value here.
ここの d 値に注目してください
D, I can think of as saying whether a car is in what lane.
d 他の車がどの車線にいるかを考えてみます
Got it.
了解
So we're pulling,
センサーフュージョンを引っ張ってくるわけですね
sensor fusion is the vector of-.
どのベクターでしたっけ?
It's a vector of double.
double のベクターです
Got it. And so the outer vector is storing like a list of,
了解そして 外側のベクターは
basically, car parameters for each car on the road.
道路上の各車両のパラメーターリストを格納していて
And then, the inner vector is each of those parameters.
内側のベクターがその各パラメーターになるわけですね
So sensor fusion I is going to be the I-F car on the road, is that right?
sensor_fusion[i] は道路上の if の車になるんですね?
Yes. And also, in the readme,
はいまた readme にも 異なるデータ
it kind of has this template of how you can access all the different data for that.
すべてにアクセスする方法を記述したこのテンプレートがあります
Got it. So I'm guessing sensor fusion index I,
了解sensor_fusion[i][6] は
index six is the, well, obviously,
道路上を走行する if の車の
that's the sixth value of the I_F car on the road.
6 番目の値になるということですね
And the sixth value, I'm assuming is the D value in Frenet coordinates.
6 番目の値は Frenet 座標の d 値になるのではないですか
Yes, and ends up being the D value.
はい 最終的に d 値になります
Okay. Now, we have the D value and we're going,
OKd 値があって
we're running a four loop over all of these cars.
これらのすべての車両に 4 ループを実行します
So basically, for each car,
基本的には それぞれの車両に対して
we're starting out a block in the loop by saying what's the D value of that car.
その車両の d 値によってループ内のコードのブロックを開始するのですね
Right.
そうです
Okay.
OK
The D value will tell us what lane the car is in.
d 値はその車両が走行している車線を示します
Got it.
了解
I don't care about the car,
この場合 車両が
in this case, if it's in our lane.
私たちの車が走行する車線にいるか いないかです
Got it.
了解
So, we have our lane and we're just trying to see if it's in this range or not.
これが私たちの車線です そして その車両がこの範囲内にいるかどうかを確認しようとしています
If D is less than two plus four times lane plus two,
d の値が 2+4*lane+2 より小さいかどうか
and D is greater than two plus four times lane minus two.
また 2+4*lane-2 より大きいかどうかを確認します
There is this plus two and minus two difference
範囲に +2 と -2 の差があります
in the range because each lane is four meters.
これは各車線が 4 メートルのためです
So we're trying to see, for instance,
たとえば その車両が
if it's in that center lane,
中央の車線にいないかどうか
is it between four and eight.
つまり 4 から 8 の間にいないか確認しています
Got it. So we could just say is the car at six,
了解つまり 6 の値を指定することもできるけれど そうすると
but that would only give us the middle lane.
認識できるのは真ん中の車線にいる車両のみになるわけですね
Right.
はい
We could just say, is the car at two plus four times lane,
2+4*lane の値を指定すると
that would give us any of the lanes but it would only give us the center value basically.
いずれの車線にいても認識できるけれど 車両がその車線の中央にいる場合のみになるわけですね
Got it. So if the car is kind of in that lane but off center
了解車両がその車線にいるけれど中心を外れている場合
we're going to need to check this range to see where the car is.
このように範囲を使って車両の位置を認識する必要があるということですね
We could even make it narrow curve if we want.
必要に応じて狭いカーブにすることもできます
We could make it narrower if we want.
必要に応じて狭くすることもできるのですね
Yes.
はい
Man, too fast too furious.
まいった すごい勢いで進みますね
So if it is in my lane,
車両が自分の車線にいる場合は
I'm going to check out the speed of the car.
その車両の速度を確認します
Okay.
OK
I can pull that from vx and vy,
3 番目と 4 番目の要素になる
which is the third and fourth elements,
vx と vy から引っ張ってきて
and then check the speed.
速度をチェックします
So I'm just calculating the velocity magnitude of it.
そして速度の大きさを計算します
Okay, so we're pulling the x velocity,
OK x の速度と y の速度を引っ張てきて
the y velocity and then we're running essentially the distance formula.
距離式を実行するんですね
Well, not quite, yes,
ん 少し違うかな
essentially the distance formula to get the-
距離式で得られるのは
Yes, just to get that magnitude of that vector.
そう そのベクターの大きさですね
To get the magnitude of this vector.
このベクターの大きさを得るのですね
Because we have the vx, we have the x and y components
vx があり そのベクターの x と y の成分はありますが
of that vector but we want to try to get the magnitude of it.
ここではその大きさを得ようとしています
Right.
わかりました
And then, we do a check_car_s is equal to sensor fusion of
check_car_s = sensor_fusion[i][5] を行います
this Fifth Element and that's the s value of that car
この 5 番目の要素と車の s 値は
that's going to be pretty important to know whether
車両と私たちの車との距離がかなり近いのかどうかを
that car is really close to us or not.
識別する際に非常に重要になります
Got it. Now, for each car,
了解ここで各車両に対して
we have- if it's in our lane,
その車両が私たちの車が走行している車線にいる場合
then we look further and if it's on our lane, then,
さらにその車両の速度と
we will get what it's speed and what it's s coordinate in Frenet coordinates.
Frenet 座標での座標を取得します
Yes.
はい
Okay.
OK
That speed part actually turns out to be
速度の部分は実際
helpful for actually predicting where that car will be in the future.
その車の今後の位置を予測する際に役立ちます
Okay.
OK
What is this line doing here?
この行は何をしているのでしょうか?
This check_car_s+=?
check_car_s+= の行ですか?
Yes.
はい
If using the previous points,
前のポイントを使用すると
we can project the s value outwards in time.
s 値を時間内に投影させることができます
Okay. All right.
OKわかりました
Why would we want to project the s value outwards?
なぜ s 値を投影させるのですか?
Because if we're using the previous path points,
前のパスのポイントを使用する場合
we're not quite there yet.
そこにはまだ到達していないからです
Okay, got it.
OK 了解
Our car is still a little bit under that.
私たちの車はそれより少し手前にいます
Okay.
OK
So we actually kind of want to be looking at what the car will look like in the future.
このため その車両が未来のどこにいるかを知りたいわけです
Because if we're using the previous path points,
前のパスのポイントを使用すると
our path represents a future,
パスは未来を表しますが
but we're looking at this current snapshot of where our car sits and all the other cars,
私たちは私たちの車とその他の車両の現在の位置を示すスナップショットを見ています
so from the perspective of the previous path,
このため 前のパスの観点から
we want to say where those other cars will look like in the future.
その他の車両の未来の位置を知りたいわけです
Okay.
OK
Yes.
はい
All right. So we're looking at where the car is in the future.
わかりました未来の車両の位置を探しているんですね
Okay.
OK
And then here we're just doing some more logic to
ここでも少し論理を展開して
see if our car s is close to this other cars_s.
私たちの車 s が他の車両 s に近づいていないかどうかをチェックします
So if the check_car_s is greater than car_s if it's in front of us,
車両が私たちの前にいるときに check_car_s が car_s より大きく
and if the gap is smaller than, let's say,
またそのギャップが 30 メートル未満の場合
30 meters, then we need to take action.
措置を講じる必要があります
Got it. So if our car in the future is going to be
了解未来で 私たちの車と特定の車両との
within 30 meters of this particular car in the future,
車間が 30 メートル以内になった場合は
then we need to take action.
措置を講じる必要があるということですね
Yes.
はい
Got it.
了解
So we need to do some logic here.
つまり ここで論理を展開する必要があるわけですね
It'd be great to lower our speed.
速度を落とすといいですよね
You could even try to flag to say we want to change lanes.
車線変更を促すフラグを設定することもできますね
Okay.
OK
In this simple case,
シンプルな例ですので
I'm just going to try to set the reference velocity down to 29.5.
リファレンス速度を 29.5 に設定してみようと思います
Okay, all right. All right. Let's try it.
OK いいですねいいですねやってみましょう
All right. Let's go ahead and save that.
了解では保存しましょう
I
ああ 保存して
don't think you saved it actually.
なかったように思います
There we go.
保存し直します
Awesome. Thank you, David.
素晴らしいありがとう デイビッド
You're welcome.
どういたしまして
Okay. Here it is. There you are.
OKビルドできました実行します
Here we go. Okay.
行きますよOK
Okay. So it's still exceeding the max jerk at the beginning,
OKまだ冒頭で最大ジャークを超えていますね
so it's still going from a cold start to 50 miles an hour, but that's okay.
まだコールドスタートから時速 50 マイルになりますが いいでしょう
That wasn't the problem we're trying to solve here.
今 解決しようとしている問題ではありませんでしたから
The problem we're trying to solve was, the problem was-.
今 解決しようとしている問題は
Can we stop before we hit that yellow car?
例の黄色の車両に追突する前に停止できるかということです
Got it. It did say something about a collision there.
了解衝突の警告が表示されましたね
Yes, it looks like-.
はい 見えました
It didn't look it hit anything but- okay,
しかし衝突はしなかったようですね OK
so it looks like it got up that yellow car, now it's going down.
黄色の車両に追い付いて そのあと速度を落としたようですね
Yes.
はい
It sees that yellow car 30 meters ahead or within 30 meters,
黄色の車両が 30 メートル先または 30 メートル以内に見えたので
and it's slowing down.
速度を落としました
Yes, it saw that yellow car.
はい 黄色の車両を認識しましたね
We told it to go 29 and we never told it to speed back up again.
私たちの車には時速 29 マイルの指示は出しましたが 速度を元に戻す指示はしていませんでした
Got it. Okay.
OK
So, we detected it.
ということは 認識できたわけですね
Okay. Yes. Okay, let's see.
OKはいOK では
I still want to solve the cold start problem.
コールドスタートの問題も解決したいのですが
Okay.
OK
How do we do that?
どうしたらいいですか?
Well, let's actually look at how we can do that.
では そちらも見ていきましょう
So here, all along,
ここでは
we've kind of been saying either go the set velocity or change instantly to this.
速度を設定するか すぐにこの車線に変更するかのいずれかの指定になります
Really what we want to be thinking about it like,
実際に行いたいと考えているのは
"Can we do an incremental change of our velocity?"
「徐々に速度を変更できないか?」です
Okay.
OK
Because we want to go at some acceleration,
たとえば 5 メートル毎秒毎秒で
maybe it's five meters per second squared, for instance.
加速させたいとすると
Then, we need to be either adding or decrementing onto reference velocity.
リファレンス速度を追加するかデクリメントさせる必要があります
So instead of just saying we'll go 29.5,
そのため 29.5 と指定する代わりに
I'm going to comment that out and I'm just going to set
コメントアウトして ここに too_close を指定する
us a flag here that says, "You're too close."
フラグを設定します
And then down here,
次に ここで
I'm going to be looking at that flag.
そのフラグをチェックします
And if it's too close,
接近しすぎている (too close)
I'm just going to be subtracting some constant value,
場合は固定値の 0.224 を
0.224, from the reference velocity.
リファレンス速度から引きます
And it's not a magic number, well,
この数値は特に意味があるわけではありません
it ends up being around five meters per second squared,
おおよそ 5 メートル毎秒毎秒になる数値で
which is under the 10 requirement.
要件 10 に記載されています
Got it.
了解
So, I don't fully understand how will this slow down the car at the very beginning.
この設定でどのように車が冒頭で速度を落とすのかよくわからないのですが
This looks like it only deals with slowing down
別の車が前方に接近してきた場合に
the car if the car pulls up on another car in front of it.
減速するだけのように見えます
Yes, there's one more thing that we need to do in order to address that,
はい そのために もう一つやらなければならないことがあります
which is to come up here and start at, let's say,
ここで開始速度を
zero miles per hour.
時速 0 マイルにします
Got it. So we're going to start at zero.
了解これで 速度ゼロでスタートするわけですね
Let's see how we can speed up,
どのように加速するか見てみます
and that's actually included in our logic down here.
実際にコードに含まれています
Got it.
了解
If the reference velocity is less than let's say 49.5,
リファレンス速度が 49.5 より小さい場合
I'm just going to be adding onto it.
ここで加算します
Got it. If it's too close,
わかりました開始点では
and at the beginning,
前方に何もないため
it's not going to be too close because there won't be anything in front of it,
if(too_close) の設定では接近しすぎ (too_close) にはなりません
it's just starting from a cold start with a bunch of road in front of it, but then, else,
コールドスタートで走り出しますが
if the reference velocity is below the speed we want to go,
else if でリファレンス速度が目的の速度以下の場合は
then start accelerating but accelerate slowly, basically, is what you are saying.
ゆっくりと加速するよう設定している ということですね
Exactly.
そのとおりです
Now, this will be doing that increment every cycle.
これによりサイクルごとに増分が行われるようになります
We could be more efficient with that.
これをもう少し効率よくすることができます
We could come down to our pack planner where it's
パスプランナーを見てみると
going through every point and be changing reference velocity there.
ポイントを通過するごとに参照速度を変更しています
Got it. How does the reference velocity
了解ここのリファレンス速度は
here affect the way points that get calculated later?
後で計算されるウェイポイントにどのように影響するのですか?
Yes, so that actually affects our end value if we come down here.
はい 最終値に影響します 下の方を見てみると
We pass it to it.
ここで渡しています
It's right here.
ここです
We're using reference velocity.
リファレンス速度を使用しています
That was tricky. I didn't even see that.
これはトリッキーでしたね気付きもしませんでした
Yes. If we're actually adding or subtracting from reference velocity in this loop,
はいこのループ内でリファレンス速度の足し算や引き算を行う方が
that would actually be a lot more efficient.
ずっと効率的になります
Got it. Okay. All right.
OKわかりました
So let's see. Should we run it and see how it goes?
では 実行して実際に確認しますか?
Sure.
はい
All right.
OK
All right. Let's take a look.
OK見てみましょう
There it goes.
行きますよ
Man, I thought it wasn't going anywhere for a second.
いやあ 一瞬 動かないのかと思いましたよ
Yes.
ええ
All right. Let's see.
OK見ていきましょう
But the battery died on it.
バッテリー切れなのかな
All right. So here we go. You can kind of see-
OK進み始めましたどうかな
It's working its way up to that 49.5.
うまくいきましたね 49.5 まで行きました
Got it. All right.
やったやりましたね
We didn't see any big red flags at the beginning there
開始の時にも赤字の最大ジャークの
for exceeding max acceleration or jerk.
超過警告は表示されませんでした
But now, here is the interesting part.
しかし ここが重要な部分です
Can we slowly decrease our velocity?
ゆっくりと減速できるでしょうか?
Okay.
OK
And we are.
そして 減速していますね
Our path is getting awfully close to the white car,
私たちの車がかなり白い車両に接近していきますが
but the car, the black car,
車は 黒い車は
our car, the ego-vehicle, did not-.
私たちの車なんですけど 自車は
Did not crash into the white.
白い車に追突しませんでした
And there it goes, slowing down again.
そして ほら 再び減速しています
All right, cool. This is awesome. So if we just waited for 15 minutes,
OK やりましたね素晴らしいです15 分待っていたら
would the car make it all the way around the track?
車はトラックを一周しますか?
Yes.
はい します
Awesome. But, of course,
素晴らしいしかし
it would be better to try and pass this white car.
この白い車を追い越せたらもっといいですよね
Yes. So maybe let's see how we can start thinking about lane changes.
そうなんですでは 車線変更について考えてみることにしましょう
Let's see. How can we start thinking about lane changes?
はい 車線変更について考えてみましょう
This comes up a point of why I really loved the spline library as well.
ここでまた 私の好きなスプラインライブラリの登場です
Okay. Sorry. All right,
OK失礼よし では
how do we think about lane changes?
車線変更についてどうしたらいいでしょうか?
When do you want to change lanes?
いつ車線変更させたいですか?
When a car ahead of you is going too slow and it's safe to change lanes.
前の車の速度が遅過ぎで 車線変更をしても安全なときです
And we have some logic to check if a car is going too slow, right?
車を減速させるかどうかをチェックする論理がありましたよね?
We do. We slow down. We already showed this.
ありました私たちの車を減速させていますこれは先ほどやりました
If the car, in the future,
車間が 30 メートル以内になる場合
is within 30 meters of where we're going to be in the future, then we slow down.
私たちの車を減速させます
Okay, so maybe let's execute some code right there then.
OK ではそこで何らかのコードを実行します
Got it. If a car, in the future,
了解未来に 私たちの車と
is within 30 meters of where we're going to be in the future, change lanes.
任意の車両との車間が 30 メートル以内になる場合 車線を変更するんですね
Yes.
はい
Got it. Okay. How do we do that?
OKどうしたらいいですか?
Here, let's just go ahead and say if lane is greater than zero,
ここで lane が 0 より大きい場合は
we start out at lane 1.
lane 1 で走り始める とします
Just that center lane.
あの中央の車線です
Let's say that lane is equal to zero.
中央の車線はゼロ とします
So what should that do?
これでどうなるのですか?
That should actually make us do a left turn.
これで実際には私たちの車は左折します
So if we are in the middle or the right lane,
つまり 中央の車線または右車線にいる場合は
basically, slam over to the left lane as fast as we can.
ささっと素早く左車線に移動するということですね
I can't imagine what could go wrong.
これでうまくいくはずです
In this case, we're just blindly going to be turning left.
この場合 やみくもに左に行きます
Got it.
了解
Regardless of if there's cars. Yes.
他の車両が左にいても いなくても行きますはい
Okay. All right. So let's see.
OKわかりましたでは やってみましょう
So, we're going to make this and okay-.
make でビルドします
All right, I keep thinking it's not going anywhere.
OK また動かないと思ってしまいます
Yeah. Okay, so let's get a good angle.
まったくOK 見てみましょう
I definitely don't want to take this one to the drag races yet.
この車は まだドラッグレースには絶対に出したくないな
Not yet. OK, so the car is just doing its thing.
まだですねOK うまいところ走っていますね
We've seen this before.
ここは前回確認しました
It's just driving in its lane.
車線内を走行しています
You think it's still going to pull up behind
また白い車の後ろにつくのでしょうか
the white car or it's going to pull up behind a different car this time?
それとも今回は別の車になるのでしょうか?
Looks like it's that red one.
あの赤い車のようです
It's going to pull up behind the red car?
赤い車ですか?
Yes. Wow. OK. Let's see what happens.
はいおお OKどうなるか見てみましょう
Here's the red car and we're pretty close.
赤い車が近づいてきましたよ すごい かなり近かったですね
But that was a pretty good lane change.
しかし かなりみごとな車線変更でしたよね
It didn't violate jerk limitations.
ジャークの制限も違反しませんでした
It just kind of shifted. The spline really helped out with that.
シフトした感じでしたねスプラインがかなり役立っていました
It was interpolating between where the car was and 30 meters ahead in that left lane.
車がいた位置と 30 メートル先の左車線のあいだに入り込んでいました
Got it. Show me the code where that happened.
了解車線変更が起きた部分のコードを見せてもらえますか
Where exactly was the spline interpolating the lane change?
スプラインでは正確にはどこに車線変更を挿入していたんですか?
Definitely. So we changed the lane right here.
もちろんです車線はここで更しています
If we come down here,
下の方へ下がっていくと
you'll notice that lane is part of this that we're adding on to for the spline.
あの車線はこのコードの一部で スプラインに足したところです
Instead of saying six is the lane,
車線を 6 とせずに
because you have two plus four times lane,
2+4*lane にしたため
when lane goes from being six to being
車線 6 から 車線 2 に移動するとき
two because the middle of the zeroth lane is two meters out from the waypoint.
中央の 0 番目の車線はウェイポイントから 2 メートル離れているため
So, lane goes to being two.
車線は 2 になる
So, two plus four times zero is two.
2+4*0 は 2 ということですね
So that's how the d coordinate winds up being two.
d 座標によって 2 になるわけですね
Exactly. Got it.
そのとおりです了解
Okay. And so then the spline waypoints are being set.
OKスプラインのウェイポイントが設定されていて
So maybe the current waypoint of the car is at d equals six, but then,
車の現在のウェイポイントは d = 6 の位置だけれど
the waypoint 30 and 60 and 90 meters out is going to be at d
ウェイポイント 30 60 90 メートルと進んでいくと
equals two and the spline will fit a
d = 2 の位置になり スプラインは
polynomial starting from zero but then shifting over.
ゼロから開始する多項式に合わせ  次にシフトするわけですね
It will be smooth and continuous.
滑らかで連続的になります
Yeah, and smooth and continuous because of the spacing too.
はい また滑らかで連続的なのは間隔の配置のおかげもあります
If you were to decrease it from 30 meters,
30 メートルより少なくすると
that lane shift could be a lot more aggressive.
先ほどの車線変更もかなり急激な車線変更になります
Got it. Wouldn't want that.
了解それはやめておきます
Yeah. OK, cool.
そうですねOK 素晴らしい
So this is pretty good. We kind of figured out now how to do a basic lane change.
とてもよくできましたこれで基本的な車線変更の計算ができました
What about some of the finite state machine stuff that
行動プランニングのレッスンで見た
we saw in the behavioral planning lesson?
有限状態機械についてはどうですか?
Right. How would we incorporate that?
そうですねどのように組み込むことができますか?
We're doing something pretty simple for doing our lane shift.
車線変更はかなりシンプルなコードで行っています
Right. Really. We might actually want to think about looking at other cars
はい実際には 最初に その車線にいる他の車を確認する方法を
in that lane first using similar logic to seeing if there is a car in front of us or not.
考えたいと思います 似た論理を使用して 前方に車両がいるかどうかを確認します
Going back to Frenet,
Frenet に戻って
we can actually just check if a car is in that lane or not and then we can check
その車線に車両がいるかどうかをチェックして
if it's in some gap range of s. If it is,
次にその車両が s のギャップ範囲にいるかをチェックすることができます
then it's not safe to do that lane change.
範囲にいる場合は 車線変更を行うのは安全ではないということになります
And maybe if it's not safe to go left,
また 左が安全ではない場合は
we can try to go right instead. Got it.
右への変更を試みることができます了解
So you could have a lane change left,
左への車線変更 右への
lane change right, keep lane,
車線変更 現在の車線の維持をすることができて
and you would never enter like lane change left if you
また左への車線変更の際に
saw that there was another car within like 30,
前方 30 メートルか 100 メートル以内に別の車両が見える場合や
maybe 100, meters in front of you or 50 meters behind you or something like that.
後方 50 メートルに別の車両が見える場合は車線変更を行わないというようなことですね
Or if you're already in that leftmost lane.
あるいは 既に一番左の車線にいる場合は
You don't want to go off the road.
道路から外れない
Right, OK. So you'd start to add some logic
そう OK有限状態機械でこれらの各状態に
around when do you shift to each of those states in the finite state machine.
シフトするときのコードに論理を追加するところから始めるのですね
Exactly. Got it.
そのとおりです了解
OK. Cool. That sounds good.
OKいいね いいねいいですね
I feel like that kind of gives us
このプロジェクトをどうやって開始するかという点で
a good sense of how do we get started with this project.
いいヒントになると思います
I mean, I think that would be a passing implementation of the project.
プロジェクトに合格できる実装になるだろうという意味です
Some of those lane changes might wind up colliding
車線変更によっては衝突する可能性があるため
so you might need to be careful about that.
そのあたりに注意する必要があるかもしれません
Blind luck. It gets pretty close.
さっきのはただのまぐれですかなり近かったです
So, maybe let's move from that
ここで そろそろ
to answering some of the questions that students wrote in about.
生徒の方からの質問に答えていきたいと思います
Yeah. And in the meantime,
そうですねそのあいだ
maybe just watch the car drive.
ドライビングを見ることにします
That was weird. Why did it change lanes all of the sudden?
あれ変ですねなぜ突然 車線が変更しているんだろう?
Did it see something ahead of it? I wonder.
前方に何かありましたか?なぜだろう
Maybe there was a car behind it that it thought was going to run into it.
後方に車両がいて 衝突しそうだったからかも
I mean it wasn't a dead stop because there was a car right behind it.
真後ろに車両がいたため 完全停止していなかったからかも
I feel like it's because we didn't reset something on the C++ side.
私は C++ 側でリセットしなかったからじゃないかと思います
That's probably true.
たぶん そうかもしれません
Now we're in the far left lane and we can't do anything.
私たちは一番左の車線にいるため これ以上何もできません
We're stuck because all we know how to do is change
行き詰ってしまいましたね ここでできるのは
lanes left if there is a lane to our left.
左側に車線があれば左に車線変更することです
Yeah. Oh man, so we need a better finite state machine.
そうですねそう ですから解決できる有限状態機械が必要です
A good cost function.
適切なコスト関数ですね
And a good cost function. Yes, right.
適切なコスト関数 はい そうですね
Try to look into the future and see what's the best lane to be in five seconds or so.
未来に注目して 5 秒後あたりに走行していると最適な車線はどれかを探してみてください
Great. So let's go to questions.
そうですねでは 質問に行ってみましょう
We've got similar questions from several people.
似たような質問を複数の方からいただいています
The first question we got a bunch of times in various forms from Sebastiano in Italy,
最初の質問は イタリアにお住いのセバスティアーノさん
from Jason, from Chris Edwards,
ニューヨークにお住いのジェイソンさん
from Nadia in New York,
クリス・エドワードさん ナディアさん
from Francesco Fantause in Italy,
イタリアにお住いのフランチェスコさん
from Michael in New York,
ニューヨークにお住いのマイケルさん
give a sort of walkthrough in order to face the project.
表現は違いますがいろいろな方からプロジェクトを開始するにあたってウォークスルーに対する質問がきています
It seems that the lesson and project lacks connection.
レッスンとプロジェクトがうまくつながっていないようです
Even in the lesson, important parts are overlooked and concrete examples are missing.
レッスンでも重要な部分が見過ごされていて 具体的な例が示されていません
Very disappointed this time in how the course was structured.
今回のコースの構成にはがっかりしました
Lots of expectation, lots of delusion.
期待が大きく だまされたかんじです
Well, let it never be said that we don't give you the straight truth from Udacity.
本当のことを示していないというわけではないんですが
We're sorry about the disappointment.
がっかりさせてしまったことは申し訳なく思います
We do think it's a really fun project.
私たちは非常に楽しいプロジェクトだと思っています
There may be some work we need to do in order to help
レッスン部分とプロジェクトをうまくつなげるための努力が
connect parts of the lessons to the project.
必要かもしれませんね
But in general, path planning is one of the most difficult parts,
ただし 一般的にパスプランニングは最も重要な部分の 1 つであり
if not the most difficult part,
自律型自動車の開発において
of autonomous vehicle development.
最重要部分になります
And so, it does make sense, it's a lot of work.
ですから 非常に多くの作業があるため 皆さんの言っていることはよくわかります
We want to try and connect it and make it a little easier.
私たちも皆さんに理解いただけるよう努力したいと思います
Hopefully, the walkthrough we just did kind of gives you
先ほど終えたウォークスルーで プロジェクトへの取り組み方
a sense of one way to approach the project.
の感覚を得ていただけたらと思います
There are a bunch of different ways to approach the project.
プロジェクトへの取り組み方は ひとつだけではなく いろいろあります
When I did the project,
私がやったときは
I approached it a little bit differently than Aaron did.
アーロンのやり方とはちょっと違っていました
Aaron's drawing with the N and the D was a little much for me,
アーロンの描いていた n と d は私にはちょっと重かったので
so I tried a different approach.
別のやり方にしました
But I think at a high level,
思い返してみると
at least what I wanted to do with the project when I first
私が初めてプロジェクトに取り組んだ時にやりたかったことは
got hold of it was just get the car moving,
少なくとも車を動かすことだけでした
and that you can do with the code from the classroom,
そして これはクラスルームのコードで達成することができます
then get the car to drive in its lane and
次に 車を車線内で走行させること
that turns out to be a surprisingly difficult problem.
これはやってみると驚くほど難しい課題でした
You can get it driving in its lane pretty well with just Frenet coordinates,
車を車線内で走行させるのは Frenet 座標だけで行うことができます
and then the somewhat harder problem is smoothing the path,
さらに難しいのはパスを滑らかにすることです
and I think there's a question coming up about
これについては質問が来ているようなので
smoothing so we'll talk more about smoothing there,
その時に詳しく説明することにしますが
but that's what we did with the spline and in this particular walkthrough.
今回のウォークスルーではスプラインを使ってパスを滑らかにしました
And then once you get the car driving in its lane,
車線内で車をうまく走行させることができると
then you enter a world that looks a little bit
行動プランニングのレッスンの終わりにある
like the quiz at the end of the behavioral planning lesson where,
ちょっとクイズのような世界に入っていくことになります
basically, you've got your car on a lane and
基本的には 任意の車線を走行させる
a few other lanes and you're looking at how do you switch between lanes.
別の車線で走行させる そして車線を変更させる方法を探していくことになります
And one way to do that,
これを行う方法の 1 つが
probably the preferred way, would be to build a cost function.
コスト関数を構築する方法で おそらく やりやすい方法になると思います
That's not what we did here.
これは今回 使用した方法とは異なります
Here we had just a very basic,
今回は非常に基本的な方法を用いました
if you see a car ahead of you, veer to the left.
前方に車が見えたら 左に進路を変える方法です
But overall, you probably want some sort of cost function that
ただし 全体的に見ると おそらくコスト関数を使用するのがよいでしょう
took into account what the cost of being in each lane is,
コスト関数では各車線でのコストを考慮に入れ
and then if you kind of work backwards all the way to the prediction lesson,
予測レッスンまで逆行して作業していきます
you can actually try and predict out into the future
すべての車両が異なるポイントで走行する未来や
where all these cars are going to be at different points in the future and what's
異なる状態 異なる車線でのコスト計算など
your cost going to be for being in different states and different lanes in the future.
その未来を試行しながら予測することができます
And so, that's kind of how you might think about,
つまり どう考えるかです
is kind of start by getting the car moving and
まず車を動かすところから始めます
that's just trajectory generation basically,
これは基本的にはトラジェクトリーの生成です
and then you start to think about
次に 行動プランニング
behavior planning and what state do you want to interchange,
どの状態を入れ替えたいのか
lanes left, change lanes right,
左へ車線変更するのか 右へ変更するのか
keep your current lane, and then if you make it that far,
現在の車線を維持するのかなどを考え ここまで到達したら
predicting out into the future and trying
未来を予測し
to figure out where other vehicles are going to be,
他の車両の進路計算を試みます
would say a Gaussian Naive Bayes classifier or a different type of
ガウスナイーブベイズ分類器や他の種類の分類器を使って
classifier and using that to decide where you want to be in the future.
未来で走行させる位置を決定していきます
So, with an actual path planner,
実際のパスプランナーでは
the way the data flows in is you get the data,
データの流入に合わせてデータを取得し
you try and predict where things will be in the future,
物体の未来での位置を予測
then you try and make your own decisions in behavior planning,
そして行動プランニングで自分なりの決定をして
and then ultimately you generate a trajectory.
最終的にトラジェクトリーを生成します
For this project, you might almost want to work backwards and start
このプロジェクトの場合 逆向きに作業するとよいでしょう
with building a trajectory and assuming no other vehicles
トラジェクトリーの構築から開始して 他には車両がいないと仮定します
are there and then start to assume
次に 他の車両も想定して 行動プランを構築
other vehicles are there and build a behavior plan but don't worry about the future,
します ここでは未来を気にする必要はありません
and then maybe worry about the future and start predicting
そのあと 未来を想定に入れ 他の車両が
out where other vehicles are going to be in
未来で走行している位置の予測を開始します
the future and I think that is where do you want to go.
おそらく この順序で考えていくとよいでしょう
That's my take on it.
というのが私からのアドバイスです
What do you have to say, Aaron?
アーロン あなたからは何かありますか?
No, I think that sounds very good.
いいえ そんな感じでとてもいいと思います
We were definitely just dealing with the trajectory for the time
トラジェクトリーについてずっと説明してきましたが
being but a cost function would be
コスト関数は 車線を変更したり
great for dealing with how to change
クイズを解いたりする場合に
lanes and the quiz is a great place to really get started with that.
非常に便利だと思います
And Frenet is very helpful for
また Frenet もとても役に立ちます
just being able to look at
道路上の他の車両すべてを
all the other cars on the road and seeing where their s, n, d is at.
観察し その s, n, d の位置を確認することができます
Frenet gets a little tricky when we're doing
Frenet はトラジェクトリーを作成するだけの
just pure trajectory generation that's
場合は少し厄介ですので スプラインを
why I kind of had that spline come into play as well.
登場させました
Got it. Cool. From Tim Tobi in New Jersey.
了解いいですねニュージャージーにお住いのティム・トビィさんからの質問です
Review implementation of spline.
スプライン実装について説明してください
So we mentioned a little bit in the walk through what a spline is.
ウォークスルーでスプラインについて少し触れました
It's basically, a piecewise polynomial function.
スプラインは基本的に区分的な多項式の関数になります
That's where the pieces are tied together at
そのアンカーポイントまたは Knots と
those anchor points or sometimes they're called Knots.
呼ばれるところで複数のピースが束ねられます
And in some Math is done and tying together those pieces so
そしてそこで何らかの計算を行いピース同士を
that the connections with the knot are
結び付けます これにより 結び目 (knot) の付いた連結が
smooth which is why the spline trajectory looks smooth.
スムースになります スプラインのトラジェクトリーが滑らかになるのはこのためです
I think for the perspective of- from the standpoint of this lesson,
このレッスンの観点からいうと
you don't really need to know how to implement it.
実装方法は知らなくても構いません
We're really just using it because the code was written in, was there.
記述されたコードが用意されているので 単純にそれを利用してください
It was really easy to use.
使い方は非常に簡単ですので
And so, all you really need to know how to do is use it.
覚えるのは使い方だけです
You want to walk through it just real quick the different parts of using it,
使い方の違いも非常に簡単に素早く学ぶことができます
there are only like three commands to run when using-.
使うときに実行するコマンドは 3 種類のみだからです
Yes, you just initialize it.
そうです 初期化するだけです
Let's actually go here maybe in the code and look really quickly at-.
実際にコード内のスプラインをちょっと見てみましょう
Sure.
そうですね
How you use the spline.
スプラインの使い方について見てみます
Yes.
はい
So here this is when you're declaring at-
tk::spline s; を宣言している
Tk spline s.
か所です
Right, so we included the header pulse and now we can declare the spline.
ヘッダーパルスを含めて スプラインを宣言します
s.set_points.
s.set_points です
You're setting the points so these are the-.
ポイントを設定しています
x and y.
x と y ですね
The anchor point to the knots around which the spline gets formed, and then-.
Knots に対するアンカーポイントで スプラインが構成されています
And then from there it's just S and then some x value.
そして ここからは s と x 値です
Got it.
了解
So you give the spline an x value you get back the corresponding y value on the spline.
スプラインに x 値を与え これに該当する y 値をスプラインで受け取ります
Yes.
はい
Cool.
素晴らしい
One of the things you do have to be careful
スプラインで気を付けなければならないこ
about with spline is just like you would have to be careful
との 1 つは 五次多項式やその他で
about with a quintic polynomial or anything else is
注意すべき事項と同様
that if the spline starts to go vertical you can
スプラインが垂直になり始めたら 同じ x 値の複数の y 値
wind up with like multiple x values or multiple y values for the same x value.
や複数の x 値で終了することです
And that starts to break things.
ここから壊れ始めます
And so that's why Aaron did that basis-.
このため アーロンはあの基礎を作ったのです
The double polymerization transformation?
二重の重合転換?
Right.
そうです
Yes.
はい
So that you're shifting horizontally.
水平にシフトしています
Makes the math easy.
計算が簡単になります
Yes. That way, if you shift the spline so it runs horizontally instead of vertically.
はいそうすると スプラインをシフトする場合に垂直ではなく水平に走るようになります
Then, there won't be multiple y values for an x and once you pull
1 つの x に対して複数の y 値にならないので
out the waypoints you need from the spline you can shift those waypoints back.
スプラインから必要なウェイポイントを引っ張ってきたら そのウェイポイントをシフトバックすることができます
Yes.
はい
And everything will just work.
これですべてうまく動作します
So we have a question from Doug in Redwood City,
レッドウッドシティにお住いのダグさん
and also from Juan Pedro in Munich,
ミュンヘンにお住いのフアン・ペドロさん
from Konstantin in San Francisco,
サンフランシスコにお住いのコンスタンティンさん
and Oliver Hagger in Atlanta.
アトランタにお住いのオリバー・ハッガーさんからの質問です
Can you talk about some strategies for
複数の計算で作成した複数のトラジェクトリーを滑らかにする
smoothing the trajectories between the calculations?
戦略を教えてください
I'm able to generate a smooth trajectory by
ウェイポイントをベースにしたスプラインを作成することで
creating a spline based on waypoints around me.
滑らかなトラジェクトリーは生成できます
However, my jerk often exceeds the threshold when I create
ところが 次の計算で新しいトラジェクトリーを作成すると
a new trajectory in the next calculation. Cool. So why don't you tell-
ジャークがしきい値を頻繁に超えてしまいますわかりました
The previous path points I would say is
前のパスのポイントを使用するのがいいと思います
a great way and that really helps you avoid any discontinuities.
前のパスのポイントを使用すると途切れを避けることができます
You've got to be careful when you're purely just creating a new path every single frame.
単一フレームにそれぞれ新しいパスを作成している場合は注意が必要です
And having those previous path points really
前のパスのポイントは
helps give you an anchor or reference to work from.
作業の元となるアンカーやリファレンスに再利用できます
And I found that when I was having problems with
また 私自身 ジャークの問題が発生したときに もっと前のパスのポイントに
my jerk that I definitely need to rely more on the previous path points.
依存させないといけなかったんだと気付きました
Got it. So one technique for smoothing is
了解トラジェクトリーを滑らかにするテクニックの 1 つとして
the previous path points or using the previous path points
前のパスのポイントを使用すると
so there's more continuity between the new path and the old path.
新しいパスと古いパス間の連続性を得ることができます
Yes.
はい
There's using the spline itself and picking out
スプライン自体を使用して スプラインに沿って
waypoints along the spline because those are guaranteed to be smooth.
ウェイポイントを拾い出します こうすると必ず滑らかになります
You could do quintic polynomial generation like it's
五次多項式の生成リンクでもできます
covered in the trajectory generation lesson,
トラジェクトリー生成のレッスンで説明しています
that involves a little bit more math.
この場合 計算がもう少し増えます
And if you're a lazy engineer that spline header files awfully tempting.
面倒くさがりなエンジニアの方には スプラインヘッダーファイルが断然お勧めです
In my case, I use the spline as well.
私の場合もスプラインを使用しました
But I also, instead of doing this kind of trigonometry that Aaron does
また 私の場合 アーロンが DNN およびスプラインから
with DNN and in projecting from the spline onto a triangle,
三角形への投影で行った三角法は使用しませんでした
I basically went through, once I create,
代わりに スプラインから
once I pulled off the 50 waypoints from the spline,
50 ウェイポイントを引っ張り出したら
I basically went through and verified that none of them were too far
速度が速くなり過ぎないよう 離れすぎている
apart to create a velocity that was too high.
ポイントがないか確認を行いました
And if they were then I pulled them back in.
離れすぎている場合は元に戻します
That's probably a little bit less efficient than the math Aaron did,
アーロンの行った計算に比べ効率性には欠けるかもしれませんが
but I could wrap my head around it a little more
こちらのやり方で少しだけ簡単に
easily and it would- I think it's a little,
できました 少しだけね
I think it's guaranteed to work a little better whereas-.
それでもうまくいったと思いますよ
Oh, yes.
ええ 成功してましたよ
I'm still not convinced this is actually guaranteed.
本当に保証できるかというと実は確信がないんですが
It seems like it does work.
うまくいっていたように見えました
Yes.
はい
And that's probably 90% of the battle.
90% はうまくいったと思います
Good practice.
勉強になりました
I have to really sit down and go through the math just
本当に保証できるコードなのかどうかについては
to convince myself whether it's guaranteed to work or not.
確信が持てるまで腰を落ち着けて計算を見直さないといけないと思います
From Doug in Redwood City California.
カリフォルニア州レッドウッドシティにお住いのダグさんからの質問です
When I used the live help feature,
ライブヘルプ機能を使用したとき
one mentor said that I should convert the waypoint map
1 人のメンターの方からウェイポイントの地図座標を
coordinates to vehicle coordinates and use this for all my calculations.
車の座標に転換して それをすべての計算に使用する必要があると指摘されました
Do you think this is a good approach?
これが適切な方法なのでしょうか?
I couldn't figure out how to do that transformation.
この転換のやり方がわかりません
Yes. I think that's an awesome approach and that's
はい私は素晴らしい方法だと思いますよ
actually- if you're talking about the local transformation,
ローカルの転換に関しては 実際 今回のウォークスルーでも
it's exactly what we did in our walk through here-.
まったく同じ方法を用いています
Let's see. Can we see the code here?
ではここで確認できますか?
Yes sure. Let's take a look.
ええ もちろん見てみましょう。
First we transform back,
まずここで転換していますね
I know this kind of going to be low.
そして下の方へ行きます
Yes, that's the transform back.
はい そこで再転換しています
But if there's a math the kind of just do the shift and rotation.
ただ シフトと回転を行うだけの計算になります
And I believe that when we're first doing it
最初に行ったのはシフトが先で
we're doing the shift first and then the rotation.
そのあと回転だったと思います
And we can kind of scroll up here and check that out as well.
スクロールアップして確認してみてください
Yes.
そうですね
So we're doing the shift first here and then the rotation.
ここでシフトを先に行ってから 回転しています
I found that to be very helpful for a number of reasons.
これには非常に便利な理由がいくつかあります
First of all, we're deploying that in MPC,
最初に これは MPC に展開しているため
and that made the math a lot easier.
計算が非常に簡単になります
And also makes sure that you don't get any functions that are
また 垂直に近くなったり 急上昇したりする
near vertical and that could just kind of explode on you.
関数にはならなくなります
And for what I was doing to try to fit points to
ポイントをスプラインに合わせようとしていたので
a spline that actually made it a lot easier because,
この作業がかなり楽になりました
then, I'm just working with the x axis.
作業しているのが x 軸のみだったためです
I don't have to try to create some separate line going
角度のある別の線を作らず
at some angle and then work from that.
そこから作業できます
From Hsin-Cheng in Taiwan.
台湾にお住いのシン・チェンさんからの質問です
How does the Finite State Machine work with hybrid A* in this project?
このプロジェクトで有限状態機械はハイブリッド A* とどのように連携するのですか?
I think we had a debate about this early on.
これについて以前 議論したと思います
I think I won that debate. Did I win that debate?
たしか 私が勝ったと記憶しています私が勝ったのでしたよね?
Yes, I believe so.
はい そうだったと思います
Oh, I'm winning. So is hybrid A*,
そう 勝ったんですこのプロジェクトに
does a hybrid A* makes sense to use for this project?
ハイブリッド A* を使うのは意味がありますか?
No. Hybrid A* makes sense more so like in a parking lot environment.
ないと思います ハイブリッド A* は駐車場などの環境の方が適しています
But, on this kind of highway,
今回のような幹線道路では
a cost function makes more sense.
コスト関数を使用する方が道理にかなっていると思います
Yes. I mean, the thing about the highway is it's a very sparse environment,
はい
so there are just a ton of different maneuvers you could
幹線道路の場合は 物体が非常にまばらな環境のため
make and you just want to choose the lowest cost maneuver,
非常に多くの戦略が考えられます そのなかで 最も低コストな戦略を
whereas hybrid A* tends to work a little better in
選択します 一方 ハイブリッド A* は選択肢が
denser environments where you have a more limited number of choices you could make.
限られる密度の高い環境により適していると言えます
And also discretized choices.
また 離散化された選択肢などです
And this is more of a continuous environment.
これはより連続的な環境になります
You could like map a grid to the highway and use hybridized star,
幹線道路にグリッドを配してハイブリッドスターを
and maybe it would work,
使用したらうまく行くと思いますが
but using a cost function or finite state machine seems to be a better choice here.
コスト関数か有限状態機械を使用する方がここでは適切な選択のように思えます
I think that maybe the broader point is in general,
その方がより一般的な見方ではないかと思いますが
I'm not sure that you would generally use
その人により有限状態機械とハイブリッドスターを
a finite state machine and hybridized star together.
併用する場合もあるかもしれません
Maybe there's some interesting way to do it.
やってみると意外と面白いかもしれませんね
There's probably some research paper out there that does it but
それを行っている研究論文もおそらく発表されていると思います
I can't think of why you would do that off the top of my head.
ただ なぜそれをするのか理由が思いつきません
I'd be very interested if someone did use that strategy.
誰かがその戦略を使用しているなら 非常に興味があります
Okay. Chris Edwards in San Diego in highway_map.txt why is "s" not redundant?
OKサンディエゴにお住いのクリス・エドワードさんから highway_map.txt で「s」が冗長になっていないのはなぜですか?
It's so easily calculated, right?
非常に簡単に計算できますよね?
Just include it in both, just in case.
万一に備えて両方に含ませています
Also, there's that map waypoints s that we're fetching at the very beginning,
また 冒頭の方でフェッチしている地図のウェイポイント s があるため
so that's used in the helper functions.
ヘルパー関数で使用されています
Okay. That actually seems to me like it might be a little bit of work to calculate it.
OK計算するのが面倒なように私には思えます
You definitely could. You'd have to do some vector math though.
間違いなく可能ではありますただ ベクターの計算をする必要があります
Or you could use one of the helper functions to get the s.
あるいは いずれかのヘルパー関数を使って s をとることもできます
Okay. You're given the helper function.
OKヘルパー関数があるんだね
S is included all over the place.
s はいろいろなところに含まれています
Yes, fair point. Fair point.
はい そうですね大事な点ですね
It's in the localization data.
ローカライゼーションデータにも含まれています
It's in the map waypoints.
地図のウェイポイントにも含まれています
From Ivan Danov in London,
ロンドンにお住いのアイバン・ダノーブさんから
can we use Frenet for both trajectory generation and behavior planning?
Frenet をトラジェクトリー生成と行動プランニングの両方に使用できますか?
When to convert back to global Cartesian coordinates and how to
グローバルのデカルト座標に戻すタイミングと
avoid jerk caused by inaccuracies from the conversion?
変換の誤りによるジャークを避ける方法を教えてください
So I think you can use Frenet for both trajectory generation and behavior planning.
トラジェクトリーの生成と行動プランニングの両方に Frenet を使用できると思います
For trajectory generation, you're ultimately going to have
トラジェクトリーを生成する場合 最終的には xy グローバル
to convert back to XY global coordinates.
座標を元に戻す必要があります
And so, how exactly you avoid the jerk
ジャークを避ける方法については
gets back to what we're talking about a little earlier, and smoothing operations,
先ほども話しましたが パスを滑らかにする
and whether how exactly you read off the spline,
スプラインを正確に読み取る
and what you do to minimize the jerk between the waypoints and the spline.
ウェイポイントとスプライン間のジャークを最小化するなどですね
From Juan Pedro in Munich,
ミュンヘンにお住いのフアン・ペドロさんから
how to deal with the lack of precise acceleration readings from the simulator?
シミュレーターの加速表示が不正確なのですがどのように対処すればよいですか?
Would inferring it from a set of consecutive points in the trajectory or
トラジェクトリー内の連続するポイントセットから推測したり
measuring time between simulator updates and using changes in speed be sufficient?
シミュレーターの更新間隔の時間を測定して速度の変化を使用すればよいのでしょうか?
Or are we better off just forcing end/start accelerations to be zero when
トラジェクトリーを計算する際に終了/開始の加速をゼロに強制して
calculating trajectories and only stitch together trajectories by their ends?
トラジェクトリーの端どうしをくっつければよいのでしょうか?
Checking out the acceleration values within your code can be really helpful.
コード内の加速値をチェックしてみてください
In the simulator, it's actually just averaging it from like a certain time,
シミュレーターでは一定の時間 恐らく 1 秒間隔くらいで平均を求めているだけですから
So it's a little bit of an average right there.
実際にはそれは平均なんです
But, if you're doing like that trajectory generation itself,
ただし そのトラジェクトリー生成自体を行っている場合
such as the quintic polynomial solver,
五次多項式解法など 一般的には
generally, you're using zero acceleration for both the start and the end.
開始と終了の両方でゼロ加速を使用しています
Yes. I think in general if you want to guarantee that you're not going to exceed
はい一般的に 絶対に加速制限を超えないようにする場合は
the acceleration limits then calculating it and verifying that in your code is helpful.
計算を行ってコードで検証すると役に立つと思います
Yes.
はい
But as you saw Aaron's code worked fine
見てきたようにアーロンのコードでうまくいっているので
assuming some things about the spline, and it just kind of work.
スプラインに関連しているのではないかと推測します
From Oleg in Austria,
オーストリアにお住いのオーレグさんから
how do we generate trajectory in state transition function (when we
状態遷移関数でトラジェクトリーを生成する方法を教えてください
want to calculate cost for each possible next state)?
(可能性のある次の各状態のコスト計算をする場合)
If the state is PLCL and we generate trajectory with horizon five,
状態が PLCL (左へ車線変更の準備) で水平 5 でトラジェクトリーを生成する場合
which states should we take for the next steps?
次のステップにはどの状態をとるべきですか?
If you want to change lanes you can calculate
車線変更をする場合は 別々のアンカーポイントを使って
a few different candidates splines by using different anchor points,
いくつか異なる候補のスプラインを計算できます
and you can calculate the jerk on each of those splines,
その各スプラインでジャークを計算してから
and then select the spline with the least jerk.
ジャークが最も少ないスプラインを選択します
That's kind of what's gone over in the trajectory generation lesson.
トラジェクトリーを生成するレッスンで説明しました
You could use jerk minimizing trajectory,
ジャークを最小化するトラジェクトリーを使用することもできます
which is covered JMT,
JMT に説明されています
which is covered in that lesson as well,
そのレッスンでも説明しています
although that uses a quintic polynomial which is different than what we did here.
ただし 五次多項式を使用するため 今回のウォークスルーで説明したものとは異なります
Do you have any clever answers to how
トラジェクトリーの状態遷移関数での生成について
to generate the trajectory first state transition function?
何かよいアドバイスはありますか?
Yes. I mean, I like the idea of using several different anchor points and then
はいいくつか異なるアンカーポイントを使用して 実際にそれぞれの
trying to actually calculate the acceleration change on each of those.
加速変化を計算するというのはいい案だと思います
That's definitely interesting.
興味深い方法ですね
From what we're doing right here we're just kind of
今回行ったのは 微調整に
had some sort of meter distance that we
使用できるメートル距離を持たせ
could use to kind of tweak and that would actually
車線変更があまり急激に
change how aggressive our lane change was.
起こらないよう変更しました
That ended up working pretty well for me.
うまく調整できたと思います
But, once you have that working from
ただし 低レベルでうまくいったら
a low-level then you can kind of build up and define higher states,
車線の維持や左へ車線変更の準備など
like keep lane, and prepare lane change left.
より高い状態を積み上げて定義することができます
And then, you're talking about
次に その行動プランニング
that behavior planning quiz and having
のクイズ コスト関数の使用
a cost function that goes along with that and with the horizon.
水平を持たせるという順序で進んでいきます
Got it.
了解
From Oleg in Austria,
オーストリアにお住いのオーレグさんから
what logic should be implemented
状態 PLCL/R (左/右へ車線変更の準備) の背後に
behind state PLCL/PLCR (Prepare Lane Change Left/Prepare Lane Change Right)?
実装すべき論理は何ですか?
If target lane's speed higher,
目的の車線の速度の方が早い場合は
then should we increase speed or track gap first?
速度を増やすべきですか? あるいは進路ギャップを先に増やすべきですか?
What if we increase speed and collide with a car ahead?
速度を増やした結果 前の車に追突する場合はどうしたらいいですか?
If target lane's speed lower,
目的の車線の速度の方が遅い場合は
should we decrease speed before a lane change or shift and then decrease speed?
車線変更の前に速度を落とすのか 変更してから速度を落とすのか どちらですか?
There are so many options.
非常に多くの選択肢があります
I think the safest is to decrease speed, generally.
一番安全な方法は 一般的には速度を落とすことだと思います
If you're trying to get over in this lane you pick out a car
この車線に移動しようとする場合 車両を選び出し
that you want to just kind of merge right behind.
その車両のすぐ後ろに車線変更をします
Yes. So the main reason you would use Prepare Lane Change is if you
はいPrepare Lane Change を使用する主な理由は
want to shift left but you can't because- or shift
左に車線変更したいまたは右に車線変更したいが
right but you can't because there's a car where you want to shift.
別の車両がいるため変更できない場合です
And so that's where predicting out into the future and using what
まさにここを予測するわけです
was taught in the prediction lesson becomes helpful because you can
予測レッスンでの内容が役立つ部分です
see whether that car that,
左側で並走していて
say, sitting off to the left and blocking your ability to shift lanes,
自分の車の車線変更を妨げている車両
is that car speeding up?
この車両が速度を上げるのか上げないのかを予測します
In which case, If you maintain constant speed a gap will
その車両が速度を上げる場合 こちらは一定の速度を保っていれば
open up for you to slide in or is that car slowing down,
車線変更できるギャップが開きます その車両がスピードを落とす場合
in which case, maybe you want to speed up if you can and get around it.
可能であればこちらが速度をあげれば車線変更できます
But, essentially, you're just kind of predicting out the future and trying to figure
基本的には 未来を予測して ギャップができるタイミングと
out when a gap will open up for you and what the best way to fit into that gap will be.
そのギャップに移動する最適な方法を計算します
So there are a few different options.
このため 選択肢がいくつかあります
Yes. Kind of the meat of the project and really where it can get quite interesting.
はいそれがプロジェクトの要点で 醍醐味となる部分ですね
Right, right. From Clio,
そうです そうですクリオさんから
I'm confused about some codes from main.cpp where in the function of int NextWaypoint,
main.cpp のコードに戸惑っています int NextWaypoint の関数の部分です
I don't know what the angle variable represents for,
角度変数が何を表しているのかわかりません
and why the angle has to be larger than pi/4?
なぜ角度が pi/4 より大きくなければならないのですか?
It would be nice if you could explain a bit about,
もう少し詳しく教えて頂けると助かります
how does the next waypoint function work?
NextWaypoint 関数の役割を教えてください
So for that one, the angle is actually the car's angle and that's just telling you,
角度とは車の角度であり
basically, which waypoint the car is looking at.
基本的には車の進行方向にあるウェイポイント示しています
We want to avoid getting a waypoint that's close to
車の位置に近いが進行方向とは
the car but that the car is not even looking at it.
異なるウェイポイントは避けたいわけです
And basically that pi/4 that 45 degrees is kind of telling you that range to look at.
また 基本的に pi/4 つまり 45 度は進行方向の範囲を指定しています
So there's a little bit of trig involved in there for just
ここでは三角法が関係してくるのですが
seeing if that waypoint aligns with that angle or not.
そのウェイポイントがその角度に合っているかを確認しています
From Chris Chan in Detroit,
デトロイトにお住いのクリス・チャンさんから
what are the key software components to use for the project?
プロジェクトに使用する主なソフトウェアコンポーネントは何ですか?
For example, JMT, cost functions, FSM?
JMT コスト関数 FSM などですか?
What do we need to pay special attention to
速度加速やジャーク制限の違反を避ける場合
avoid violation of speed acceleration and jerk limit?
特に注意すべき点は何ですか?
So the key things that we used were
ここで使用した主なものは
Frenet coordinates and some sort of a path smoother,
Frenet 座標と パスを滑らかにするもの
whether it's a quintic polynomial or a spline or something else.
五次多項式かスプライン あるいはその他のものですね
And then, a finite state machine to figure out what maneuvers you want to take.
また有限状態機械を使用して戦略に応じた計算を行います
So I think that's probably the minimum set of things you can do but you can get kind of
最低限 これだけは必要だと思いますが
infinitely complex and particularly
無限に複雑にすることもでき 特に
adding states and trying to navigate through traffic as quickly as possible.
状態を追加してできるだけ早くトラフィックを操作することも可能です
From Konstantin in San Francisco,
サンフランシスコにお住いのコンスタンティン サンホセにお住いのジャン・フランソワから
Jean-Franois, did I say that right?
発音は正しかった?
I hope, in San Jose.
大丈夫かな
Can you suggest how JMT and spline should be used together to achieve a solution?
ソリューションの達成に JMT とスプラインを併用する方法について教えてください
I would say it's probably either or. What would you say?
私はどちらか一方だと思うのですが どう思います?
Yes. I think it's either or.
はい私もいずれか一方だと思います
Basically, you're looking to smooth
基本的にはパスを滑らかにしようとしているので
a path and you can use JMT or a spline to smooth that path.
JMT かスプラインのいずれかを使用すればいいと思います
From Frank Schneider in Germany,
ドイツにお住いのフランク・シュナイダーさんから
please explain what to use as data in the getFrenetMethod?
getFrenetMethod では theta に何を使用すればいいですか?
The heading of the car produces off s values when more distant coordinates are converted.
距離のある座標を転換すると 車の進行方向によって外れた s 値が生成されます
That's probably because of the non-linearity of
それは転換の非線形性が原因と思われます
the transform and we're seeing that kind of at those certain edge cases of
私たちも進路の特定のエッジで確認しています
the track where if we have this kind of S and
この種の s と d 値を使用すると
D value they are calculated close to when the car is at that edge.
車がそのエッジ付近にいる場合 値が近接して計算されます
It might just be a little bit off.
少しだけ外れているだけかもしれません
Got it. I didn't implement that plan, Aaron.
了解僕はそのプランは実装しなかったけどね アーロン
You can always change the mask too.
mask もいつでも変えることができますよ
From Friederich, how to calculate s_dot_dot?
フレドリックさんから s_dot_dot の計算の仕方を教えてください
S is going to be our position in Frenet coordinates.
s は Frenet 座標で私たちの位置になります
S_Dot is going to be our velocity infinite ordinates.
s_dot は私たちの速度無制限の座標になります
S_dot_dot is going to be our acceleration infinite coordinates.
s_dot_dot は私たちの加速無制限の座標になります
So if you think about how to calculate S_dot which is velocity,
速度となる s_dot の計算方法を考える場合
basically, you want to figure out one point and then another point.
基本的には 1 つのポイントを計算してから次のポイントを計算します
And then, we know the vehicle operates at
すると 車が毎秒 50 ポイントで走行する
50 points per second or the simulator operates at 50 points per second.
またはシミュレーターが毎秒 50 ポイントで動作することがわかります
So if you divide the distance between
ひとつのポイントから
one- take the distance from one point to another point, excuse me,
別のポイントへの距離をとったら (失礼)
and then divide that distance by
その距離を 0.02 で割ります
0.02 which is 50 points per second that should give you the velocity.
これが毎秒 50 ポイントになり 速度がわかります
So that gives you S_dot. And in order to calculate
s_dot が得られますs_dot_dot を計算するため
S_dot_dot what you want to do is calculate the change in velocity.
速度の変化を計算します
So you want to calculate the velocity between one pair of
つまり 任意のポイントとポイント間の速度と
points and the velocity between another pair of points.
別のポイント間の速度を計算するわけです
And then, divide them by the time it takes to get
そしてすべてのポイントを通過するのにかかった時間で割ると
across the entire set of points and that should give you S_dot_dot.
s_dot_dot が得られます
And it would be the same in XY coordinates.
xy 座標でも同じです
It's just a coordinate transform.
単純な座標の変換です
Thanks so much for joining us for the walk through the Path Planning Project.
パスプランニングプロジェクトのウォークスルーにご参加いただきありがとうございました
This is a really challenging project.
これはかなり難しいプロジェクトですが
It can also be a really fun project.
同時に 本当に楽しいプロジェクトでもあります
You can do a lot of neat stuff with it.
かなり巧妙な実装が可能です
The work Aaron's done to build the simulator for
このプロジェクトやこれ以外のプロジェクトでも シミュレーターの
this project and for a lot of the other projects is really really fantastic, I think.
構築に費やされたアーロンの努力は素晴らしいものがあります
It makes the project a lot more fun than it
アーロンのおかげでプロジェクトは
would be if it were just decimals on a terminal screen.
期待以上に楽しいものになりました
So I hope you have fun with it. I hope the walk through we did here gives you
皆さんも楽しんでいただけると思いますこのウォークスルーでプロジェクトにどのようにアプローチすべきか
a sense of one or maybe multiple ways to approach the project.
感覚を得ていただければ幸いです
And we'll be in Slack and on the forums
私たちは Slack およびフォーラムにいます
and amenable to answering more questions if you have them.
質問があれば答えていきたいと思いますので
So, let us know if you do.
ぜひ 質問してみてください
Yes. Cool! Buh-bye!
はいということで さよなら バイバイ!